Was
da
jetzt an Präsentation ist.
Viel Konferenzzeit hier.
Hält noch stand. Komme ich zu euch
oder
soll ich mich irgendwohin setzen?
Nein, du kommst. Rück doch damit.
Was sollten wir jetzt gucken?
Ich wollte gucken. Man kann ja die
whole PDF als auch das machen, oder?
I
have no control.
There's a remote up there. I will open the presentation for you.
Which is yours?
I'm just
the moderator, so I don't have any presentation. All is fine.
Ja.
Ja, that's already up.
Do you do the introduction to the session?
Yes, I do that.
Ja.
Welcome with us.
Yes.
Okay.
Das ist heute 7:30 Uhr.
Aber was ist final? Woher soll ich das wissen?
Nein, weil Franziska gestern meinte, sie hätte es noch gestern, glaube
ich, oder heute Morgen heruntergeladen.
Hier steht 7:30 Uhr.
Da musst du bei Franziska hineingucken. Du kannst es nicht.
I think this is the remote control, ja?
Ja.
And is there also a pointer? Ja, okay.
So the pointer is here and back and forth is here.
Hi.
I'm Caitlin. I'm presenting for Jessica Horn.
Oh, okay. So we have two Caitlins at that session.
Oh, two Caitlins. Okay.
Yes, because we have another Caitlin, but she will come in a
second.
Okay.
Caitlin Horn. Ja.
Yes.
Okay. So you are the fourth.
Frederick is this one.
Hi, Mara. Hi. Hi, I'm Nora. Mara. Nice to meet you.
And you are from?
Ja, it's Mara without the E.
So the German are the lucky ones, so they add the key E to the end.
Hello. Hi.
Stinka, the second one. Yes. You are from the
. I probably misread, but... Like a relationship.
I just get a pen and a paper and write down some things.
Here we don't need a-- Oh ja, that's what I wanted to ask.
Do we need the microphone or can we use this one?
It's the cost to
determine.
Ja, online.
That's why.
So Caitlin, are you giving the first presentation here today?
Okay, then maybe you should already get one of those.
Yes, but there...
Hi. Hallo.
Hallo.
Questions after that.
Ja, I will.
Then after each talk.
I mean, if we have time, we can make one question after the talk.
Usually we have the discussion.
Then we ask all the speakers to come up.
There is one online presenter.
Oh yeah.
And can he
zoom as well if he wants?
It's just a Zoom.
No, he's only online.
Online?
Yes.
Because I got videos as well.
Yes. That online, that we take
a question, for example.
I'm not a data person, so it's all very tiring.
Ja, exactly. Imagine if you had it all from one to the other speaker.
From the remotes.
Where are these things? I've not seen them.
Five minutes, two minutes.
Thank you. He ran away.
Ja.
I like it in my name.
Oh, is that all?
Yeah. I don't know. They have to ask him.
What if no one?
No, there will be.
There will be.
We didn't expect so many at all.
I think we'll come.
Very good.
Do
you want to
before?
You up.
Yes.
Yeah.
Because they have been here on Tuesday and--
I can write something by myself.
I guess, yeah. Okay.
If not, I will write something. It's also-- Yeah, I have to miss the...
But
you can check.
So, yes.
No, but
you can ask him which kind of presentations, then he will
show it to you.
Thank you.
And they have been involved with movies or?
Yes.
So the proper signs are lost, but I
will show five minutes and then...
So five minutes will be shown after 10 minutes.
Yeah.
So if you have a 10-minute-
If you are already done, 10 minutes in.
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
Questions or if you still have to decide.
Gotcha.
Yeah, and we have already signed. It's been 10 minutes in.
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
So the signs don't start until 10 minutes.
Yes.
So then, yeah.
Yeah, we have enough time.
Questions are welcome. So at the end of the session, we are going to make time for
some questions as well. So if you have time, we will talk.
Hello.
Good morning to everyone
to the Session 29 of the symposium, From Cabinets
to Clouds: Bridging the Gap Between Collection and
Database Management.
For the beginning, I wanted to give a short introduction into
what we envision for this symposium.
And
we thought
about the topic From Cabinets to Clouds, how physical
collections and digital data workflows
connect. Is it okay with the mic?
Closer.
Closer?
Sorry. Okay.
Because we're working in the Natural History Museum in Berlin-- Oh, yeah, I forgot
to introduce ourselves. So this session was organized by Caitlin
Thorne, who's the first speaker today, me, Frederic Berger,
who's online, Mareike Petersen, here in the first row,
and Sabine von Mering, also in the first row.
So if you want to get in touch, we are all working at the Natural
History Museum in Berlin.
And as I said, so we are dealing with
physical collections and want to know
more about digital data workflows, how different
institutions have different workflows, who works
together with whom, who decides, who has the
responsibilities in the end to facilitate
digitization workflows. Because at the end, we all have one shared
goal: to align the collection expertise, the digital
practices, and to create high-quality
interoperable biodiversity data.
We want to learn from each other what works and also
maybe what works not,
and where do we have challenges that arise, and how can
we overcome those. Key question would be here,
how can we build cohesive workflows from the cabinets
to the clouds? So with that, I want to
introduce the first speaker. It's Caitlin Thorne from the Natural History
Museum in Berlin.
Okay.
This is my last slide.
A little preview for you.
So my name is Caitlin Thorne, and I'm a
data manager at the Museum für Naturkunde or the Natural
History Museum in Berlin.
And today, I'm going to be talking about collaborative
development of an institution-wide controlled vocabulary
and how we implemented a system at the museum.
So who are we?
This is myself and my co-authors here.
We have Nora, who you just met, who is the
deputy head of Department Services for Collection Future.
We have David, a paleontologist, Sabine, who's
also here in the front row,
who is a data scientist, and we have Jessica, who is
a media administrator.
So we are an interdisciplinary working group established
two years ago to discuss solutions to a lack of
controlled vocabulary at the museum.
So different collections use different terms for the same thing.
We have around 30 million objects in our collection
and a very long history, and our collections have
developed different ways of describing their own
collections
over this time. So they often use different terms for the
same thing, or they'll use the same term for different things
amongst different collections. So the kinds of terms I'm talking
about would be describing an object type or a preparation
type, or the availability of the object.
Sorry, this is very echoey. It's quite confusing.
So what is a controlled vocabulary?
It's also known as a thesaurus.
And
a thesaurus, just to get quite technical for a minute, is an ordered
compilation of terms and their natural language
designations, which is used for indexing, storing, and
retrieving in a documentation area.
But essentially, for our purposes, it's a list of terms and their
definitions.
So the aims of our working group were to bring together the
collection, data, and system expertise.
We wanted to identify the terminology requirements
across the different collections,
and the collections already had their own vocabularies that they
were using. But we wanted to consolidate these existing
terms into one shared vocabulary that could be
used by all the collections.
We also wanted to establish a process to
review new terms and maintain
this list.
So this is our flight path. We began in January
2024 with some workshops to collect requirements,
and then a few months later, the regular meetings of the group
started, and we would meet every two weeks.
By late 2024, we had come up with the
preliminary term list,
and early 2025, we completed our tool
testing, which I'll talk a little more about later.
In March 2025, we presented our work to the
collections, and by the end of 2025, we
had the specialists from the collections review our
vocabulary.
In June of this year, we finished our regular meetings,
but we came up with a plan to maintain the group,
moving forward.
So what did the vocabulary need to achieve?
We wanted to disambiguate similar or overlapping
terms. We wanted to improve metadata consistency
across the collections, support precise searching and
retrieval, and improve interoperability.
Also, an important part of this was we needed to recruit collection staff to
share their domain expertise.
So what were we actually hatching here?
We looked at many systems throughout this process.
There are many options for a thesaurus.
For example, Cosmos,
but these would require technical setup, user training, and
financial investment.
We
researched these a lot. We had a lot of meetings with different companies
about what they offered, but we came to the point
where we decided a simple Excel spreadsheet would
work, and it would help us gain the expertise of
the collection staff.
Using an Excel spreadsheet instead of a more technical system
allowed easier accessibility for collection
staff because they're generally familiar with
Excel already.
So it took away having to learn a new system before
participating in
contributing to our vocabulary.
And once we have the Excel sheet structured, we can
always move it to a dedicated system later.
So this is what the list actually looks like.
The second column is list name. So that's kind of generally
the
list that we focused on. So you can see here there's our
availability vocabulary list, as well as
the start of our type of collection object for zoological
objects. These are then grouped into a larger category
of object-related terms.
And then we have our terms in English,
some alternative terms, and of course, because we're a German institution, we
have the German translations.
For some of our term lists, Latin was relevant, so that's
also an option. And then we have the definition
in English as well as in German, and that was a primary
focus of our working group, putting together those definitions to
disambiguate the terms. For example, you can see
here,
in the availability, the terms lost and missing
could be quite similar or used interchangeably
or used differently by different collections.
So we define lost as basically the object was lost and
is permanently gone, but missing means it's
missing, but it could probably be there and come back in the future.
So yeah, that was really a lot of the work of our group and our
discussions with collection staff to disambiguate those terms.
So we wanted one vocabulary across all the museum
systems.
All of our collections are currently being moved
into Specify, so it would apply there as well as in our
media repositories, our public data repository,
and hopefully within our internal communication and
documentation
But of course, it's really hard to implement something new
with so many people with different backgrounds.
So how could we ruffle fewer feathers along the way?
We used a trusted forum to help build support.
We needed specialist expertise from across the museum.
And luckily for us, the MFN has hosted a Collection
Cafe for around five years.
This is an internal event held every Monday highlighting
different research projects and what's going on within the museum.
And so we decided to use this forum to
introduce our project, and we think this helped increase
participation because people were already familiar with this project.
They already might have had it blocked off in their calendars to attend.
And we wanted to get as many collections staff on board as possible,
so we used this format to talk to people, and we
also sent institution-wide emails to engage people.
So, where did we land?
Following the Collection Cafe, collections staff reviewed the
terms list and definitions that we had come up with,
and the working group incorporated the feedback and made a final
vocabulary list. We also made sure the terms were
aligned with Tawankha.
We implemented the vocabulary into the Specify pick list
as all of our data is being published
through Specify as the starting point.
And we published the controlled vocabulary Excel sheet
and
made up a system for any
changes to be requested.
And we've communicated throughout this process.
So what have we learned from this? We've learned that different professional
backgrounds brought different terminology, assumptions, and
priorities. So everyone had different
aspects that they felt were most important throughout the
process, from within the working group to the
collections.
But so reaching an institution-wide solution that worked for
everyone required a lot of discussion and compromise.
But we used familiar tools to make it easier for a wider group of
staff to access the vocabulary and
participate in the process.
We used a trusted forum to give the
project more visibility and credibility,
and structured communication also built support throughout the
process.
We also think that ongoing governance matters just as much as creating
the initial term list, so not leaving the project
once the list is created, but we've established a way for people to
stay in contact with us and for us to develop the list
in the future.
So thank you so much for listening.
You might have noticed a little bird theme throughout.
So all of the images in the
presentation were taken from our new data portal.
You can scan the QR code to have a look at it if you'd like.
And this is a place where we've used our controlled
vocabulary and practice. So thank you.
Thank you, Caitlin.
Questions now? Or-
Yes. We have time for-
We have time?
... a couple of questions.
Okay.
First you, and then I come to you.
Thank you. This was very interesting.
We will be doing the same thing at Naturalis in Leiden.
I have two questions, actually.
You used an Excel sheet.
Yes.
Do your terms also come in hierarchies?
And how did you model that in the Excel sheet?
Yes. So we have
some terms with hierarchies, and we've used this higher--
We have two other Excel sheets. There are three sheets in total.
The one is this list of all the terms, and then we have
another sheet which defines the names of the lists, and
another sheet which defines the names of the categories.
Apart from that, we don't particularly go into hierarchical structures.
We didn't encounter anywhere where we needed this in the project.
Yeah. My other question was, as we will be doing a similar
exercise, and we're looking for
these definitions and how do other institutes use these, are
you publishing this anywhere, your lists, making them available?
We haven't decided to. We've published it internally,
but I'm sure we can share it. I don't think there's anything too
internal on there.
All right. Awesome.
We can send it to you.
Thank you.
Go on, Laura.
I can do it.
My question's about the governance part.
I wonder if you could talk a little bit more about that and specifically
how your museum is structured in terms of who has authority, if there's
conflicts about how terms are being used or if there are
needs that, say, the collection specialists feel are not being addressed.
Mm-hmm.
So
essentially, we
do not particularly have authority over the collections as a group, so they really
are free to choose to use this or not within their collections.
But by incorporating all of them in the process, we got a
lot of feedback on terms. And I think another key
point was we weren't very-
I would say fussy maybe on the terms we accepted.
So if the collections wanted a term, there's a 99%
chance it's in there. It was only if
we needed to disambiguate something that we discussed with them
what would be removed. So for
most cases, there are maybe a few
similar terms
because one collection uses it differently to another.
But
we
were able just to include
all the vocabulary that the collections wanted.
There are, of course, maybe cases where a collection
didn't give us feedback.
But we also have this process for making sure in the future
that anything they want in there is in there and making sure it
aligns with what's currently in there.
I hope that answered it a little bit.
Oh, we would have some time. Yeah.
Hi.
So that is interesting to see your approaches and how it's
like a bottom-up from the collections.
But have you also looked outside to existing
controlled vocabularies where you could reuse the terms for
your definitions, or was it just purely internal looking?
Do you mean from outside the institution or...? Yeah.
So after we
basically compiled all the lists from within the institution to make the
initial list and then worked on that,
after that, we looked into Darwin Core lists and made sure that they made
sense with those.
And since it's been implemented with Specify,
we
need to, I think, make sure it still aligns with
a few other things, like
some German standards, like minimal information
standards in Germany. But I think most of our terms are pretty usable
all around.
Yeah.
Thank you, Caitlin.
Cool. Thank you very much.
Yeah. We would go on with the next speaker.
It's Christiaan Steenkamp from the National Science Collections
Facility in South Africa.
Thank you, Nora, and to the TDWG organizing committee for the
opportunity to speak here today.
I'm going to just give you a little bit of a breakdown of the journey the National
Science
Collections Facility has taken in South Africa to try and bridge that gap between
the cabinets and the clouds.
Looking at advancing standard collections state documentation for institutional
continuity and coordination. Now, in South
Africa,
we currently have a network of about 23 partner
institutions that cover
national councils, museums, both provincial,
municipal, and national, as well as biodiversity institutes,
as well as citizen science networks.
And these individuals are all part of this community.
And we've been building this over the last nine years.
And the NSCF's role in this has been to support the institutions both financially
but also administratively, and in some cases, also providing
staff to the institutions to move our collections
forward. Now, interestingly enough, in South Africa, we
have a lot of issues funding-wise and things like that.
So you might find one institution having a full team of individuals that can
manage the collection, but in other cases, there's skeleton crews, and in
other cases, there's only one individual that has to do all of this.
So the talk really today is about our approach to trying to
create some sort of standard framework between those cabinets
and the clouds, meaning how can we realize some of the lost data that we
have in our institutions and make that available online that can be easily
managed going forward.
So basically,
we are trying our best to align this with international standards, while
also developing our own systems where possible.
So the Jack and Jill of all trades. As you know, many collection staff have to
juggle a lot of different things.
And in South Africa, many institutions in the NSCF network don't even have data
managers at all. So you have collection by staff that need to deal with these
issues on their own that might not be as technical as your traditional data manager
is.
So they are juggling administrative and curatorial digitization
and compliance work while
with limited time also having to keep track of the state of their collections.
And that makes it quite difficult to compare this across institutions and
help us to identify gaps and where resources
need to be allocated.
Now, collection management system cuts that friction.
It allows us to have a standard interface for capturing data,
and that's basically limited only by the schema.
So if we don't provide someone with the ability to capture a certain type of
information that gets lost or gets logged in a notebook.
Now,
the impact of management styles by different individuals or
teams or groups of that can greatly be reduced
when we give them this platform where they can all access this.
And it allows us also to get a very good baseline and remove
guesswork when we are allocating resources in South Africa.
So collection staff, therefore, don't have to be data managers per se, but they
have to capture the data and feed the system.
Within the system, we have automated processes that
guide users and assist them in moving the data along
And this can be overseen by the institutional data managers where they are
available, or by NSF staff, like myself, on a higher
level that can actually assist institutions remotely
using a system like this.
So in our collections, basically, description is in state.
So we use Darwin Core for our occurrence data and mostly in our
collections.
But collections themselves have Latimer Core,
used to standardize how we describe them, the scope and the size and the access.
But things like the collection state, things like
readiness,
the risk, and things
are not always captured or available to everyone.
So that often lives in the memory of these individuals, or in a very small group
of people, and not always in one place.
So that knowledge is current, it's real, it's detailed, and in many
cases, it never leaves that space in a shareable or comparable form.
So how do we measure the impact of this institution against that and
identify potential institutions that need something?
And M. Polanyi used to say in "The Tacit Dimension" in 1966, he said, "We
can know more than we can tell." And again, giving people the opportunity to share
it and tell opens up that world.
So in the spirit of the extended specimen, we are putting a lot of effort currently
in South Africa to extend outward,
but what about our cabinets? Should we go beyond just
describing a collection and moving towards tracking its state over time?
Now, we approached this from multiple fronts or, at least at some point, believed
that a shared
system could allow us
more visibility on operational level, more memory on institutional
level, and also,
like Caitlin said, having a shared vocabulary amongst these
institutions to speak the same language when we are referring to different things.
And the system basically captures that by allowing us to see what's
going on in the collections, but also keeping track of changes within that,
and eventually getting to that point where a very basic term here, something that
is at risk, what does that mean? What does water damage mean?
What does pest activity mean?
So how this all started was in 2021, the NSF and Natural Science
Collection Facility community all came together to create a collection management
and conservation manual, and this evolved
into a national collection assessment to measure the
implementation of the manual and understand how people were doing against these
community standards. And we went around with our taxon
experts and assessed the collections after self-moderation,
and also, along with other community members and observers,
scored these collections based on that.
And this brought us to the point we've seen that once we have this
snapshot in time, how are we going to persist this?
How are we going to measure this over time?
And we decided to tackle this problem using Google Stack,
so using App Scripts, and Google Forms, and also
Data Studio, which was Looker Studio, now Data Studio, now Looker
Studio, something like that.
Now, this system was very nice. So in 2025, we rolled this out,
and it was very much a visual-only tool that you could look
at.
And they posed some challenges there in terms of interactivity and things.
But
because of those challenges and the way that we had to manage this, we
got to the idea of that we needed to refactor the code into something standalone.
So our Google Stack pipeline basically had these
view-only dashboards, and people could drill down a little bit, but that was about
it. So it was not very interesting or engaging.
Updating the system meant you had to scroll through the whole Google Form if you
wanted to make one or two updates to some aspects of your collection.
But also, in the back end, onboarding institutions and collections
was a pain because this had to be done manually. So scaling was a very big issue.
Now in the age of agentic development, we did see the
opportunity to refactor our code base from this Google Stack into
a standalone system that could be used within South African collections that
met our
criteria for a collection status tracking tool.
Now, what I meant by the status is these three main domains of
implementation, measuring the implementation of the manual, but also
looking at institutional documentation and collection-based
documentation.
And this ties into a larger system, basically.
But it allowed us to have an assessment that could be shared
amongst all individuals, but also the ability for institutions and collections
to add or remove some of these questions and make it more unique for
their purposes. So every question basically carried the
scoring rule, and you would complete the questionnaire, and the system would
calculate your scores, the scores for implementation, your documentation
scores, as well as the risk associated with those.
Now, the enrich versus link in practice was basically
thinking and going back into the cabinets, now, which I mentioned earlier, was
how could we then expand so that we could also better manage these collections
in under-resourced places where people didn't have time or capacity to deal with
all aspects?
So the system allows you to link to the
jar, the preservation batch, the ethanol or the
formalin that you are using, but also
the conditions that the specimen are kept in.
What's the curatorial history of that specimen in the jar?
Has the temperature's been fluctuating? Was the humidity high?
Why are things evaporating very quickly?
And the system here that we've made allows you to get that.
Talking about enriching, we pull data from GBIF and surface it inside of the
collection where we allow people to make edits that are then tracked, and then
later on can be exported in an IPT-ready format and uploaded
back to GBIF for updating and ingestion.
We also have the shared lists, so categories are shared amongst institutions,
storage locations, very standard-based.
And each of these things within the system can be identified and pushed to the
whole network where required.
In terms of visibility,
users have different levels of access here that use role-level security, so
not UI enforcement. And so you have institutional admins
on high level, you have the NSCF administrators, and you have collection managers
or data managers all looking at the same data, but from a different
aspect that is important to them. Very much like a boundary object
that Star and Griesemer term, that means the
shared record and something that each community
reading it can understand while still holding enough integrity
to
coordinate all of this. And this was coined by studying a natural
history collection at the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology in Berkeley.
Now, keeping track and defining departure.
The system also allows us to keep an audit trail.
So everything you do, whether you're topping up a bottle, if you are changing
liquids or buying, all of that is tracked, which user does it in an
audit log, and that can be accessed.
We also started thinking about how could we preserve things so that institutional
continuity and institutional memory.
So keeping track of that and defining that departure means that we
also have the ability to develop unique handovers and handover
documents that pulls from the system automatically, like
contact details or passwords or certain workflows.
But it's customizable, so every institution can actually go in and make
their own handover document, which then can be kept
up to date by the individual working in the event that they might be moving on.
Unfortunately, sudden death or just general retirement.
Now, this basically is one specimen with a very rich record, and so many
systems focus on the ecological record.
But we've thought of expanding into a preservation record,
the storage environment, and also the administrative stuff.
But the system is not supposed to be competing with anything, so it can work and
works alongside Specify and BraMS, and basically allows you
to pull in those things. So if you're managing collections with Specify,
you will have a read-only access in the system.
But if you do not have access to Specify, you could also use the system to do some
management.
Now, this is part of a bigger picture that we are doing and also making this
information available to the public in the sense of transparency,
moving into things like showing our collection states, our impact
that the collections are having,
as well as
our digitization efforts in general, and moving that into a virtual
museum and a virtual library using Living Atlas platform and
access to memory for the library.
Now, this is an ongoing endeavor where we are basically looking now at
piloting this refactored system after we've had the individuals
using the previous Google Stack system, moving them over to the
refactored system at some institutions, seeing how that goes,
then broadening the participation beyond that pilot phase to all
institutions within the community,
and then formalizing and publishing our vocabulary that we are using for
the collection state in terms of implementation, documentation, and so
forth, as well as the risk.
And then hopefully we can contribute this information into a
curatorial history piece or part of the extended
specimen puzzle.
So how does your network or institutions handle this challenge?
Do you have one role that one person has to do everything, or do you have multiple
roles within your institutions that handle different aspects of this?
Do you like enriching your data or just linking around?
Do you have formal processes,
or is it an informal habit kept in their notebooks that we later on
have to page through to try and find out what's next?
That's me for today. Thanks a lot.
I appreciate your time.
We would have time for one question. Of course, in the back.
Very cool talk. How much of what you've done do you feel
like are you comparing to current TDWG standards, for
example, and the gaps that are there?
Are you
able to summarize some of those key gaps, maybe even in the new Darwin Core
data package format that you're modeling a lot of things that are pretty
cutting-edge there?
Yeah.
I do have as far as possible, tried my best to stay within
the Darwin Core system. So looking at the ability to actually create these
Darwin Core packages for non-technical staff and individuals.
I think the biggest gap that we've identified was in terms Latimer Core,
that would be very basic in terms of describing a collection.
But where the big gap here is, is what is a collection state?
What does it mean for a collection to be ready?
And that's something that I think we need to consider and talk
about because that really gives us the ability to
understand how past curators and the next generation of
curators look at a collection, not as a snapshot, but
as a journey.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Our next talk is an online talk by Frederic Berger, who's
the deputy head of the science program Collection Future at the Natural
History Museum in Berlin.
That was very interesting.
Thank you. Yours as well.
Good morning.
I am very pleased to have been invited to contribute to this
First of all, I wish to thank Sabine von Mering for introducing me to this
topic. It is her tireless work on personal identifiers and on editing
Wikidata which sparked my interest and led me to think about
strategies on how to make even more use of the already available
structured data on personal names in Wikidata.
This work is still at a strategic and conceptual stage.
We have not yet implemented a full operational workflow.
However, we hope that this approach can help address a challenge shared by many
collection-holding institutions: the absence of unique, persistent
identifiers for people in collection management systems.
I won't spend much time making a general case for persistent identifiers.
The scientific arguments are already well-established.
People are essential for linking biodiversity data.
This has been said, no specimen exists without an agent.
It is therefore sensible to focus on identifying and linking these agents through
persistent identifiers.
In this ecosystem, Wikidata can serve as an important broker.
It enables us to connect institutional databases with other
collection-related information.
To understand the scale of the challenge, we first look at the current
representation of people in Wikidata.
Wikidata contains more than 13 million items classified as
humans.
Of course, only a small proportion of these people are directly relevant to natural
history collections. As we can see in this example, Alexander von
Humboldt is, of course, one of them.
When we filter for people connected to collection-related properties, for
example, through the property collection item set
P11146, we find approximately 30,000 individuals.
Many collections hold, for example, specimens collected by Alexander von Humboldt,
like the museums in Berlin or in Paris, and of course, many, many more.
We have a look at other relevant identifier systems such as Sobodat.
We find roughly 15,000 distinct persons.
Again, Humboldt, he also has a Sobodat ID.
Looking at the splendid database from Senckenberg, the
database Entomologists of the World, we therefore find
13,500 distinct persons referenced in Wikidata.
For the Museum für Naturkunde in Berlin, we can also consider the Wiki project
MfN Berlin Names, led by Sabine von Mering.
This project focuses on people with a documented connection to MfN.
The project currently lists approximately 1,100 people, among others,
also Alexander von Humboldt.
These examples represent the result of a substantial and ongoing
community effort. Many contributors have worked to identify collectors and
other agents connected to natural history collections.
There are certainly many additional databases, identifiers, and sources that could
be included. Those three are, however, probably the most relevant
for demonstrating the relation of a person to a collection object.
More than 34,000 distinct persons is already
substantial. But is this a representative number for more
than 200 years of natural history research and specimen collecting?
Perspective. I ask the more practical questions.
How many people might we expect to find in a collection such as the
collection of the MfN?
MfN holds approximately 30 million collection objects from around the world,
collected from the 18th century onwards.
For this project, we brought together every available list containing person
names that we could identify.
The raw input consisted of around 30 tables from different
sub-collections containing approximately 800,000 name strings.
These were not 800,000 people. They included spelling variants, abbreviations,
duplicated records, and so on.
Our processing workflow therefore aimed to reduce this
noise.
By deduplication, we reduced approximately 800,000 name occurrences
to around 200,000 distinct name strings.
These strings could then be grouped into roughly 13,000
clusters. However, a cluster does not always represent a
single person. Some clusters may contain different individual similar names.
Conversely, some individuals may still appear in more than one cluster.
Therefore, this is just a rough estimate.
But based on the available data, we consider it reasonable to expect
approximately 15,000 distinct people associated with
the MfN collections.
This brings us to the central problem, the identification gap in the collection
management system. Only around 1.6% of the people
represented in our central CMS are currently linked to an unambiguous
persistent identifier.
To be fair, there are additional lists in which people have already been identified
unambiguously, but these data have not yet been integrated into the central
CMS. If we include these distributed lists, we may reach approximately
10% of identified persons, which still means that
the large majority of historical and contemporary agents remain
represented only as disconnected text strings.
So how can we bridge this gap?
One option would be to add identifiers manually, one person at a time.
This is certainly possible, but with approximately 15,000 people, it is
unlikely to be completed in the near future.
The next question is obvious: Can we automate the process?
The honest answer is partly, but full automation would probably
not be a good idea. The final act of disambiguation often requires context
that is not explicitly present in our data.
This is where collection curators and domain experts remain indispensable.
Automation cannot reliably make this final decision.
The central idea is therefore to combine the large community effort
represented in Wikidata with an institutional strategy for prioritization.
There are several possible prioritization strategies.
I would like to highlight two. Option one
is to focus first on the names that occur most frequently in the collections.
This approach maximizes impact in terms of collection objects.
In our data, approximately 1,500 agents are associated
with up to 90% of collection objects.
The exact figures may change as further data sets are incorporated, but the
general pattern remains stable. A comparatively small number of people
contributed a very large number of specimens.
Identifying these people first would connect a large proportion of collection
objects to a persistent identifier relatively quickly.
Another option could be to focus on the more complex
clusters, those containing many ambiguous strings, spelling variants, or
potentially different people.
This approach may affect fewer records initially, however, it addresses the core
problem of fragmentation and improves the quality of the underlying authority data.
Neither strategy is correct. The choice depends on institutional
priorities, available expertise, and whether the immediate objective is
broad coverage or improved data quality.
Our immediate next step is the creation of a web-based
names directory. This directory will provide a structured mapping
between a name cluster, the name strings contained in that cluster,
the presence of name in various sub-collections, and a list of
potential Wikidata QIDs. This is where the
community effort represented in Wikidata becomes
especially valuable.
By comparing name strings from our collections with Wikidata labels and
aliases, we can generate more candidate matches.
That is because we can restrict the search to people who already have known
relationships to natural history collections.
Basically, the approach is the same as using a reconciliation service, but we
are using just a subset of data to reconcile against.
That restriction does not eliminate ambiguity, but it
substantially increases the probability that a matching name refers to the correct
person. In this case, we find likely candidates for A.
White.
Chris and Jacob White do not show up yet on the list of candidates.
A collection database manager will skip these strings and
might want to let the community know that those names are not associated to
collection-related properties in Wikidata.
With the ongoing community effort, it is likely that they will show up
eventually in the list of candidates during one of the next iterations.
This directory is not intended to replace expert judgment.
Its purpose is to make expert work more efficient by providing curators with
a pre-structured, evidence-based list of possible identifiers.
To conclude, bridging the gap between name strings and
persistent identifiers requires more than technical matching.
It requires institutional commitment.
It requires clear priorities and the continued involvement of
collection experts. Wikidata and related community resources
provide a valuable foundation. Automated methods can help us
organize and prioritize the data.
This will help to reduce the complexity of the task, but reliable
identification remains a collaborative process between data infrastructure
and human expertise.
The challenge continues to be to provide experts with the right workflows.
Only then we can gradually move from disconnected name strings towards a
linked data ecosystem.
Finally, I would like to extend special thanks to Thomas Lindner for providing all
the scripts for data processing and the entire MfN collection staff for
providing the data.
Many thanks.
Thank you very much.
I heard he is not in the room until now,
but we try to get Frederik to the Zoom call room by the end
of the session where we--
Sorry?
But he's online on Woova, so you can always ask him questions there.
But managing the acoustics is just a bit challenging, but we will
find out.
Thank you.
Our next speaker is Cailin Meyer from the Smithsonian
Institute in the USA.
Okay.
Is this live? This one?
Is this mic also live? Do I need to stay away from it? Sorry. Okay. Thank you.
So Jessica was supposed to be standing next to me.
She is our data manager. Unfortunately, at the last minute, she
could not make it. So,
as Nora mentioned earlier, she does purely the data and the catalog.
I do purely transactions and acquisitions, but we work very closely
together.
So I will not be answering your data questions, but she is also online and
happy to answer any of them for you.
Okay. So, just a little bit of background into explaining
the size of our collection.
The USNM Insect Collection was established in 1881, which is
actually before the Smithsonian was established.
We house the second-largest insect collection in the
world, with an estimated 35 million specimens.
Our collection represents over 400,000 species and
houses over 130,000 primary type specimens.
Please remember that last number.
It will come up again, and this is all managed with a
relatively very small staff.
So today I'm talking to you about the difficulties
of maintaining legacy data over platforms that have essentially
aged themselves out of use, and our department's work
to synchronize and modernize them into new databases.
So on the screen, I have a page from our first version of a
database. It's the original handwritten type ledger
catalog books. So our department has been using these books
since 1896, which means they have seen 130 years
of continuous use by the department.
The type numbers are assigned in the book.
They're attached to the specimen, and then they were used in the publications.
So these books recorded information that includes that original
catalog number, the species name, the sex, the locality that it was
found at, the year the specimen was collected, who sent it to
us, who collected it, and then the date it was entered into the
ledger. And again, we regularly used these books up
to the 1990s.
But by the last physical ledger, the department was no longer recording
that last item when the data was being entered into them.
And they stopped that because, in the 1990s, or rather the
mid-late 1980s, our department built its first
electronic type database called Inquire.
It was built in-house by museum staff, and it captured
data at the level you should expect from the 1980s.
But then technology moves pretty fast.
By the early 1990s, we were already building a replacement database
system.
The museum switched to something called the Collection Records Information
System, or CRIS, in the mid-1990s.
And that was another built in-house system.
It also allowed for more relational database structure, so it could
include recording loan and acquisition information in it.
The department spent a significant amount of time transcribing paper
loans and acquisition records from the 1960s onwards
into that system. But critically, the Inquire database
was not migrated into CRIS. It was separately maintained and also
separately used. So we had CRIS doing transactions and
regular cataloging. We had Inquires for types.
The rest of the notes are not showing on the screen, so I'm not being antisocial.
And then the EMu database comes along.
Most of us here are familiar with EMu.
Inquire and CRIS were migrated into it in
2007. We've had a few years to test its use out,
and then we started using all the available
modules within it by 2011, and that included the transaction
module. We were using that by 2011.
But that did not come without its own ridiculous challenges with it.
So remember,
Inquire was a very rudimentary database.
Essentially, fields did not map well to EMu,
and we discovered issues that were so severe with the department, we
had to put a public disclaimer on any type record from Inquire,
and every record was essentially being labeled as an Inquires
type.
Additionally, Inquire could be used to contain both description
papers and literature reviews, but when it was migrated in, there
was no way to distinguish which of those was which in EMu.
So
all the newly entered types were done under the category Entomology Type
because we were also actively using EMu at the same time.
So we needed to separate the Inquires types with the bad label with the new type of
entomology collection.
So here is an EMu record for the first type specimen that
is in the ledger books. This is USNM type number one.
It was originally entered as an Inquires type.
It was marked with a status of unreviewed with the data disclaimer,
and then in 2013, it was reviewed by a specialist and
updated as from an Inquires type to an Entomology type.
But even though this is a verified record, we do not consider it
complete because it was not given a USNM
ENT barcode number,
and the specimen is also not imaged.
Then compare that to the last recorded type in the ledger books.
Work on this record has been done. It has a barcode.
It has been imaged, but it has not lost its Inquire
status because the data has not been completely reviewed, and that's because
reviewing this data takes an incredible amount of work hours.
And then here we have mapped out an example of CRIS
transactions data migration into EMu because this also did not go
terribly well.
Again, because of the mapping issues, I believe.
These records have no objects attached because that option
didn't exist in CRIS the same way that it does in EMu.
The date fields are very peculiar.
They must be checked against the original paper records, and the material
description often has incredibly limited data.
Wasps.
How many wasps are there in the world? I actually don't know that answer.
There's always almost more material description and more data
available on the paper records. So again, I am referencing original paper
records instead of actually using these legacy transactions.
So these are labeled as legacy generations
from CRIS.
And in the notes field, there's an incredibly useful string that
tells me
who created the original CRIS record.
So Norden was a technician that worked at the
museum
in the early 2000s. And then it also tells me the number where I can find the
original paperwork under.
But wait, there are even more issues that we discovered.
So since 2011, we kept running into various small
complications surrounding the primary type catalog especially.
We know that not all of our type records were cataloged in either
database, so not all of them made it into Inquire, and not all of them made it
into EMu.
We've also discovered issues with duplicated barcodes that were due
to an out-of-house printer.
We also have weird changes in a workflow that resulted
in newly acquired types not being cataloged at all,
and acquisition records then also not being associated to the type catalog
record as EMu allows. And so when we looked at all these problems
together and how do we actually fix all of them, we realized we really
needed a clean and accurate primary type inventory to solve them.
So the department created the type inventory project
for entomology specimens or types with an I.
The project is essentially a 100% specimen-level
inventory of the type collection because we have to ensure that the
data in our types database is accurately reflecting everything in
the physical collection.
We have over 130,000 primary type specimens again.
We intend for this to take place over several years and for it to be
completed over several phases.
So currently, we are deep into phase one.
So here, a curator is given the Excel spreadsheet of data that is
taken out of EMu. They're comparing that spreadsheet with the physical
specimen in the collection and noting any discrepancies between the
specimen data and the spreadsheet.
That is then returned to Jessica, and from that data,
Jessica generates a short list that's given to me that is related to
transactions and questions that the curator has about them.
So here is an example of what we consider a now complete record.
We have a digital image of the specimen.
It has its tags with it.
It matches the original ledger books correctly, and the EMu
screenshots are showing us the new inventory status and the
updated record status from Inquires to just Entomology Type.
It has a USNM ENT barcode assigned to it, and the related
type and inquire number have been properly recorded.
Okay.
So progress overall, we have almost
3,500 existing type records that have been fully
completed. We have added over 500 new types to the
catalog. As phase one is ongoing, phase two is also started.
That's related to my transactions linking.
So I'm given the list, I take that list, I conduct investigative work
into the type acquisition paperwork and the type ledger books
to resolve any of those questions.
I'm also actively matching the loan records of the holotypes we've sent out
to their catalog records so that it's all properly concluded in the catalog.
Additionally, we're having conversations with our staff to try and resolve our
known workflow issues. Why are types not being cataloged as they are
acquired? Why are catalog records not being linked in the transaction module?
And then finally, we also have, of course, run into some new questions to resolve
with this.
So in particular, two of them that I have time to talk about.
For some reason, a large number of the types have a very
specific Florida, United States locality added
to the summary string, but it is not even remotely close to
the verbatim data on the record. And then something that affects me
personally/professionally,
we have discovered some issues with the first thousand
numbers in the ledger book where the number that has been assigned does not
actually match what is in the ledger. So the type specimen will have a number.
That number matches the original publication data.
And you go back to the book and it's a completely different specimen.
So this has happened about seven to 12 times, I would say.
It's only happened within the first thousand numbers, but it is super fun.
So like I said, this is a multi-year project.
We still have significant plans for our other phases.
So along with phase two, we're developing new workflows and
procedures. So for instance, all currently uncataloged types must
be cataloged and properly linked before being sent out on loan.
To address the unpopular Excel spreadsheet, Jessica has created
a much more user-friendly online form that then inputs the data
into a spreadsheet for the user.
As phase three, we're going to be prioritizing vetting the Inquires
data as it's returned by the curator so that we can finally remove all of
those disclaimers, and we're also working on
reviewing the type citations. And then as part of the phase four,
we're sort of hoping to use these results to plan and
prepare for more imaging projects so we can get all of the type
specimens actually imaged and online.
And finally, we also want to investigate the use of AI and automated
processes to help with some of the maintenance load off of our staff because again,
very large collection, relatively very small staff that is in charge of it, so it
can be very overwhelming for them.
And that was it. Thank you. I hope there's some time for questions.
Hello. Thank you very much. Yes, there's some time for
questions.
You said that Jessica transformed the spreadsheet into the more
user-friendly web interface. Are the curators actually
accepting this? Because from my experience,
a lot of people just prefer their Excel spreadsheets, even though that makes the
processing later on a lot more tricky.
Yeah.
Does it actually work?
So the problem with the spreadsheet that we did transition to
is that it has,
doing quick math, over 70 columns in it for the type
specimens. And our technicians over
15 years have basically decided that they do not want to scroll all the
way through it for all the things to enter one specimen.
So the spreadsheet in particular just asks the information
that is very specific for the types, so they don't have to go through all these
columns to hunt for it, and then it automatically gets put into a spreadsheet
that concatenates for Jessica, and she can do a singular upload as opposed to
doing individual uploads as well.
Have we just introduced it? Hopefully, it works better.
There would be time for another question.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Our next speaker is Marije Timmermans from the Senckenberg Institute in
Mönchengladbach, Germany.
Hello, everyone. My name is Marije Timmermans, and I'm working as the
data manager at Senckenberg German Entomological
Institute, part of Senckenberg Nature Research.
And today I will talk about my role as a data manager,
and I will focus on the collection data migration.
Natural science collections play a vital role in scientific research,
yet they often rely on legacy databases.
This often limits accessibility because legacy databases
don't often allow for external
access and also don't follow
common standards.
Senckenberg decided to implement a new
collection management system, Dina.
And the goal is to provide collection data as digitally accessible,
searchable, and globally usable knowledge following the FAIR
principles,
and of course, support the continuous management of collection data.
This collection data migration comes with two main challenges
for our institute. The first is the
Senckenberg organizational challenge.
Our small entomological institute is part of a larger
organizational structure and all
institutes within Senckenberg need to align to the
CMS.
And the second challenge is
our internal institute collection management challenge.
Within our institute, we have multiple collection management systems,
subcollections and practices, and that all need to align to
the CMS.
So I will start with the first challenge, the Senckenberg organizational structure.
Senckenberg employs 900 employees.
It has eight research institutions in seven
locations in Germany.
The
Senckenberg Data and Modeling Center is a central unit
within Senckenberg, and among other things,
they are implementing and further developing the CMS Dina.
And they do this for all institutes within Senckenberg.
Senckenberg German Entomological Institute or SDEI focuses
on insect research.
It was established in 1886 in Berlin
and joined Senckenberg in 2009.
And because of this long history,
they have a very defined identity.
It employs around 35
people, including volunteers,
and it has many
donations from a private collection, which makes it an
interesting
collection for mobilization.
SDEI has two departments. The first is
systematics and biogeography.
It holds five entomological subcollections and
is led by four
collection scientific heads.
Then the second department,
this is the Information Center for Entomology,
and it focuses on the research infrastructures.
For example, our special library, our archive, and
other information systems.
It further focuses on biodiversity informatics and
data research.
I'm affiliated with the second department,
but I help both with their data management questions.
So I started in February of this year as a
data manager at SDEI,
and I am the first data manager there, and as many
documentation tasks and administrative tasks, data
management was not the priority of my colleagues.
So what do I do as a data manager at SDEI?
I create data life cycle documentation.
For example, I created a workflow for digitizing books
in our library.
I
assess legacy data structures. For example,
I created
a database diagram of the Biographies of
Entomologists of the World database that was already previously mentioned.
And we also use this database diagram
in the documentation that I'm writing.
Then I also prepare internal training materials and documentation, for
example, on data cleaning or adding resources to
our Zinkenberg metadata portal. And the overall goal
is, of course, to improve data literacy of our colleagues.
Then we move to our second challenge, the current
collection management practices at SDEI.
They
have four obstacles that
hinder us for a
smooth data migration and creating a sound mapping for
all the sub-collections at SDEI.
The first obstacle is that our collection
managers are using various collection management
tools.
Four of the five sub-collections are currently using the Corel
Paradox relational databases.
This was implemented
in the '90s, and each collection manager
has their own database instance on their computer.
Then we also have
one collection manager that copies all the changes to a card
catalog as a backup, and we have one collection manager
that
uses his own spreadsheets.
Then we have the second obstacle,
is that these separate instances and spreadsheets cause
the schemas to diverse. That means that
collection managers are introducing or have introduced new
fields,
moved the fields to different
tables, and renamed the fields
depending on the collection manager's preferences.
And these two obstacles differ from other entomological
collections in Zinkenberg,
where collection data is managed in one shared
database with one schema.
And it's important to discuss how we are going to align all the
entomological
collections when moving to the new CMS.
Then the third obstacle,
our current practice focuses on
collection management as a tool only.
Collection data as a management tool,
rather than a research infrastructure where data is shared
among researchers.
This leads to easy data entry for our collection managers.
For example, they
enter the subspecies name in the species field
because it's easier to find for them there.
But of course, this makes the data very hard to share or to publish.
And then
the fourth obstacle, which is that there's no formal data
governance in place yet in our institute.
The data ownership is not formally assigned.
Decision power over collection management has grown
historically and sometimes lies with the technical assistant and
sometimes with the scientific collection head.
There's also no formalized workflow
or documentation for the data life cycle.
Then in preparing for
the migration, I contribute in several ways.
I have a liaison role between the institute and
the data modeling center,
where Dina is implemented and developed.
Because of the physical distance as well as the
felt distance between our institute and Zinkenberg, this is
needed.
I also
get our colleagues more familiar with Dina.
I organize workshops on collection data structure.
And in my experience, because of the gap in IT
knowledge, one-on-one meetings are best to get everyone on the
same level.
I also remind them of
biodiversity information standards and open science
principles instead of focusing on internal data
management practices
that they now have.
And I'm also planning to create technical
workflows. For example,
data enrichment workflow, a mapping workflow, and
workflows for migration to the new CMS and editing
as well.
Then it's too soon to say
if my facilitating role has led to a smoother
migration.
Most importantly, I provide a link between the SDMC and
SDEI, and this will hopefully speed up
data migration at our location.
So far,
I organized meetings, proposed mappings, and
have begun to write
migration workflows.
What works for me is treating my work as a prototype.
In design thinking, each iteration
produces a new prototype that stays closer to the final product.
And I offer a way to test these functionalities.
For example, a new mapping or
functionalities within DINA.
And I let the domain specialists give
feedback on this.
This is very helpful because testing a prototype can spark new
ideas
for me as well as for the domain specialist.
And I also use these prototypes as a communication tool,
and
involving testers in decision-making
builds a sense of ownership and increases the
chances in successful migration and implementation.
So this is very useful.
Then I want to thank you for your attention and organizing this very
interesting symposium. And if you want to know more about DINA, I
recommend going to the presentation of my SDMC
colleague, Jonas Grieb, this afternoon.
It's Symposium 42A, or scan the QR
code
for the DINA documentation and some of our data
resources. And I want to thank you again, and I look
very forward to hearing about your experiences.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Since you're all really good with your time, we have time for questions.
Hey. So you mentioned that you were developing workflows for things like migration
enhancement. Who in your organization carries out that work?
Does that role fall to you? Do you have other technical staff?
Does it fall to the unit that you're liaising with?
Sorry, can you repeat the last part of your question?
Who is doing the technical work where you're mapping out the workflows?
You mean...?
So you mentioned that you're developing workflows for
migration and enhancement.
I was just curious, do you have technical staff that actually
carries out those workflows?
Does the unit that you mentioned that you were a liaison for
carry out that work?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So far, I
created or did some testing with Python
from
our
spreadsheets
to the API that DINA provides.
I do not have to know how to
create a real pipeline for this on our server, but I think that
SDMC will be able to help with this, yes.
Are there any other questions?
Just an observation. I really love that you used the word "empathize" at
the beginning of that process.
I almost feel like there's a role at TADWIG in the standards sort
of body
to standardize that kind of process to start with empathy,
to unlock, right? To make that connection between the researcher and the
person who's talking gobbledygook at the other side.
So how can we standardize empathy?
Yeah, that's a really good question.
For me personally, I don't think
that
you can standardize that as a vocabulary, for example,
but I think it's good data management practice to
really try to understand the person that you are working with, and
in my case, that will be the collection managers.
Is there time for another question, or
is there another question?
Just maybe just to emphasize that, of course, you can ask
questions to the speakers, but you can also, of course, share
your insights, your experience, to have a more
conversation. So we will have, after the last talk of Holly, a bit more
time. So I think you have heard different presentations here
today, so of course, it would be great if we could help each other, not just
questioning. So just to keep that in mind after Holly's
presentation.
Thank you.
Okay.
Hello. Okay.
Hi, I'm Holly Little. I'm the Informatics Manager in the Department of
Paleobiology at the Smithsonian Natural History Museum.
Thanks to Kaelin for giving a lot of really good background.
So see her talk for some things I'm not going to explain.
So I'm here to talk about a framework for aligning collections data with
the global data ecosystem for data creation to extension.
And this is really about implementation within a natural history
collection of all of the things that we do here at Tadwick.
To take you back a little bit, this is a graph that I put together
in 2018 for a Tadwick meeting
about the implementation of Darwin Core terms for the
mobilization of paleontological collections.
And as you can see, the implementation was very low.
We found that although a lot of collections had done a lot of work to digitize, the
understanding of how to efficiently and effectively use
Darwin Core was low, but it was mostly
because there was misalignments in understanding of what data should
go in certain fields. There wasn't terms to
represent critical data for paleontological collections, or there were
other linked resources within the data ecosystem we all work in
that would prohibit being able to mobilize a certain
data in the most discoverable way.
So since 2018, I've been on a journey
to try to resolve what this would look like.
I originally thought doing this map would just tell me where I needed to go and
enhance my data locally, but it turns out what it showed us was that there was
a broader conversation that needed to happen across the paleo community that we've
been having over these last, really, 8 to 15 years.
And now we're getting to the point where we're doing the improvements locally.
So my collection is the largest fossil collection in the world.
We have 42 million
individual objects estimated in our collection.
It's an
integrated paleo collection, so it includes inverts, plants, vertebrates,
trace fossils, sediments,
all time periods, wide geographic
coverage around the world as well.
Right now we have about 800,000 specimen records, and we
estimate that we need 10 to 13 million to fully document our
collection.
So just to give you an idea of the variety, if you're not familiar with paleo
collections.
So we have an informatics team, which up until
2025 was me. I am a team.
I've had other contractors or temporary staff for
specific projects, but only me doing the holistic picture.
In 2025, we added one additional staff person, and upcoming, which
I'll talk about in a second, we're going to add three more staff people to try to
tackle this challenge of 10 to 13 million records.
Importantly, over this time, we've really developed what our fundamentals are, and
that's to work iteratively,
be a bit image-driven, which I'll talk about.
Share data widely and often. Don't be afraid of perfection.
Just get it out there because people will help you understand what you can do to
get better data.
And of course, doing a lot of work to align with global standards,
principles like the fair data principles, and being very open access with our
data and images as well.
So how are we adding three new staff?
We were very lucky last year to receive a gift to launch a five-year
project to really tackle the concept of what a holistic,
comprehensive framework for digitally documenting a paleo
collection could look like.
It centers around
1,000 significant objects, but really what those are, are
to help identify that variety of material you have in a
paleo collection and understand what the unique needs might
be across the diversity of objects that we have.
So we're using the first 1,000 to set up those initial
objectives, determine what the item-driven workflow should be, what are the
minimum requirements, what does it mean to have readiness for all of the
different things that we're seeing in our larger data ecosystem, like AI
look like,
and to create the baseline workflows that we can adapt to then hopefully
extend to the rest of our collection in manageable
subsets based on the taxonomy, the type of material,
other descriptive things that might inform the workflow that you're using.
In parallel, also over the last eight years, the paleo community has been
doing a lot of work to evaluate the broader landscape and
understand how paleo data can be more discoverable and better
mobilized within the ecosystem that we all work with.
So how well does Darwin Core work for us?
Where are there issues in the taxonomic backbones?
Where are there resources that we could be linking to, but because they don't have
identifiers, we're not able to do that?
So for the past three years, I've been working with collaborators
like Talea Cream in the back of the room
on a grant to facilitate a lot of information
gathering and conversation to understand where the community wants
to go with this broader understanding of
mobilizing and improving the discoverability of paleontological
collections. And as part of that, we're going to have this idea of a paleo
roadmap as one of our deliverables, which is going to identify
recommendations for how we can improve different parts of the infrastructure or
recommendations to data providers for how they can better
share their data or better utilize the tools available to them.
And just to point out, there's a few presentations that relate to this work that
have happened this week.
And we have a poster downstairs also talking about it.
So what we want to do now as part of this
project is think about how we can implement the
results of this work that we've been doing as a community
moving forward as we both digitize new material and
improve the legacy data, which a lot of people have talked about this morning is a
huge challenge.
So where we're starting from
is this idea of a paleodigital framework,
and it covers the
data life cycle of the specimens in our care.
So we can't just stop at data capture.
That's largely where that issue of the first graph comes from is we did
digitization, we got the data out there, we moved on.
So really thinking about starting from data capture, doing
that in a way that enables the iterative practices that we want to get
to, incorporating new types of imaging, more efficient
imaging, and then really focusing a lot in data enhancement and
extension that ultimately then improves our mobilization,
and it loops back around in a cycle as we get feedback, as
we have that round tripping that often gets discussed as well.
And of course, underlying all of that is the ongoing data
management and community coordination and knowledge sharing because we don't work
in isolation. We want to stay in alignment with this broader global community.
Because we are talking a bit this morning about the capacity within
our institutions to do this work,
I wanted to highlight with the
increase of this informatics team, we're able to both add new
types of work in our department, but also redistribute
where some of the responsibility lies.
This is just focused on data. It doesn't talk about a lot of the other work
that the collections management team does,
but just to give you an idea of how we're going to weight some of this work moving
forward now that we'll have a larger informatics team.
And this is really new. We're still refining what this will look like
as we bring everybody on board.
So optimizing our digital framework from here.
As I said before, we're really focusing on 2D imaging, do
an imaging first mentality, and this is because we believe this is the
best way to enable downstream
improvements, workflows, and to iterate on the information that we
gather in digitization processes.
So if we take a picture of all the labels and we get at least one
documentation shot of our specimens, there's a
lot we can do to improve our data from there as new
technologies are available to us, as new requirements are coming about
in the data standards or vocabularies.
Also in the data capture process, we want to develop
adaptable specimen surveys for initial data capture
that enables that iterative process in addition to the imaging.
So rather than comprehensively documenting every detail
about a specimen on a first pass, we're trying to define for each
type of specimen what are the core data points we want to collect on the
first pass so that we can build upon that from other resources
or other enhancement workflows that can be done in
a more automated or batch process.
We also want to include critical descriptive details like
the work I presented on, on Tuesday for material entity type
to help define the next set of workflows that we might want to use
depending on the type of material we're talking about, and
also aligning to using external systems like
MIDS to evaluate where we're at with our digitization
to help define who should do which process next,
basically.
And the picture here in the bottom, sorry, I forgot to mention that.
Part of this idea of focusing on core data points, we might have
thousands of specimens with that same locality, for
example, shown in the specimen label image on the left.
We don't need to transcribe that on every label because we have one
ledger that has that locality in it.
So really figuring out how we can leverage the sources that we
have instead of being more duplicative in our
processes.
That also means that we can use new technologies.
So we are thinking a lot about how we can make sure we have the original
verbatim data captured so that
as we iterate on it and change it over time, that original
information is preserved, but then also enabling
more effective ways of doing text extraction from labels using AI
or other tools.
Where a lot of the
meat of the upcoming years of work is going to be in our data
enhancement, and this really addresses both the legacy data and
the new data. And it's where a lot of the work that we've done for the last few
years has focused on.
And
in case you're curious, we've presented a lot in TadWig over the last few years
about trying to improve things in paleo collections, specifically
related to taxonomy and a few other things.
So we want to establish data structures that officially integrate
both external data sources and add to those
external data sources because often they need new data and input from our
community as well,
and create readiness for AI and linked data,
and really enabling that use of the persistent identifiers
moving forward. So I'm not going to talk a lot about taxonomy or
stratigraphy which will come up next, but just knowing there's a lot of
challenges with fossil taxonomy in how we can mobilize our data, and
so we are now going to implement a lot of the work that we've done to try
to discern what those issues are and align
our taxonomy, for example, with external sources like Worms or the
Paleobiology Database, Catalogue of Life importantly, but also
feeding back into those systems as we implement to tell them
this one doesn't align, for example. How can we fix that?
And the same is true for geological context.
This is a really critical data class for paleo collections
and has similar issues to taxonomy of it can be a
dynamic data point. And there are resources out
there that we can leverage rather than trying to maintain our own
internal system for this. The same is true for taxonomy, which
relieves some of the burden of data maintenance for your local data
systems.
I didn't address all the other enhancement things that we want to do, but I thought
I'd start trying to list them on the bottom.
So we want to streamline georeferencing, disambiguate people data,
work on our geography vocabulary,
and so on and so forth that a lot of people have talked about this morning.
And then, of course, we want to look into data publishing.
How can we leverage the new things that are coming about with Darwin Core?
The Darwin Core data package, for example,
does a lot to give us a more dynamic way of thinking about how we
map and model the data coming out of paleo collections.
And because we do have such a variety of material, it turns out that it
isn't actually as useful to use one model for
every single thing in a paleo collection.
And last year we did a mapping exercise as they were testing Darwin Core
data package, and found that we could leverage
different modeling profiles or publishing profiles to better
represent different types of material, whether it is something that
really relies on relationships between organisms, or we
have cores that cross many different
geological horizons.
So better leveraging the
more structured data models that we now have
to map our data and get the right data points
out for researchers for discovery.
This also includes leveraging the Darwin Core material entity
type to be more specific about what our records represent,
and incorporating all the work we did in enhancement to include
links and persistent identifiers and building out our Darwin
Core
archives or Darwin Core DP publishing with the
IRI terms.
So none of this happens individually.
Like I said, we don't want to work in isolation.
We want to make sure that we're doing this in alignment with the broader global
community.
So, so far we've done this with a lot of different partners.
We have, of course, our work in our department.
We work across the Natural History Museum at the Smithsonian, across the
Smithsonian with institutional partners and with many global partners
as well, including the Paleo Data Working Group, TADWIG,
GBIF, Morphosource, et cetera.
And part of why I'm here today and kind of giving you this broad
idea of where we're going talk is we want to work with you.
We want to know what you've tried. What could we adapt
from your workflows? We want it particularly for anybody that's
working with paleo collections, what are challenges that still need to
be solved? We've done a lot of work over the last eight years to
figure some of this out, but we can't cover everything, of course.
So what challenges can we incorporate?
And because we do have this unique opportunity to have a very
paleo-focused
informatics team for the next four years,
we're in a position where we can try things, we can test stuff, pilot it,
and then push that back out into the community to get your input and
iterate on that as well.
So if you have other challenges, please let us know.
And I went through that really fast because I felt like I was running out of time,
but I'm happy to answer questions.
Thank you very much, Holly.
Are there questions to Holly directly now? Oh, yes.
Thank you. Very interesting.
You mentioned that you don't digitize localities
per se because they can be repeated.
Mm-hmm.
Can you say a little bit more how the software reflects that
workflow? Does it exist as a linkable record,
for example?
Yeah. So, we use the same collection system that
Kaelyn shared, EMu, if you were in here for her talk.
So
in EMu, we have separate modules, one that's the core specimen data,
and then a separate one that's the collection event and locality.
So we can digitize our locality records into that
module, and then link them to as many specimens that have
that identifier on them.
In practice, we are not entering data directly
into EMu. We do enter data into spreadsheets.
And we actually went through a project, our first mass digi project was
around 2017, which is what prompted that first analysis.
And we were doing transcription of every single label, fully,
completely transcribing them. And what we found is that there was a
lot of variety in how different labels
wrote down the exact same locality, and it became a
really big issue and time sink to try to
resolve. So that's where we really want to look at how can we just
pull the identifier off of the labels and then pull in the single source.
But then we do where we can compare to make sure there's not critical
differences. Yeah. Did that answer your question? Okay.
Great talk, Holly.
Thanks.
Thank you.
I was curious when you just said that, like
Would it be feasible to
completely transcribe the ledgers using AI?
Yes.
Taking images using AI, creating that spreadsheet, and
then linking the ledgers back to the
specimens just by that number.
Yeah.
And would that be
really a much faster way to digitize this collection? I'm just curious.
That's what we're hoping for. So we did a pilot project.
Because we are the size that we are and the
age that we are, we have so many different series of numbers.
This is our USNM locality card series.
So we just finished a pilot project using AI to
transcribe, do the text extraction from these just to test it.
They're mostly typed, so it was a very straightforward project.
But the goal is to do it on both the specimen labels
that you see here,
which are
super inconsistent in formatting and handwriting versus typed, and then our
ledgers to do exactly what you just said.
I think the ledgers are harder because they're lists,
and they're not super structured.
But going back to the verbatim part of this, our hope
is to use something like AI to get a block
of text represented by each of those identifiers,
no matter what series you're talking about,
that isn't parsed, it's as verbatim as possible, and then
use additional tools to parse that data out, standardize it, and
of course, have the citations to note that it's coming from AI, all of those
things. But yes, that is the goal. So at that point,
we would come back to the problem of
getting too many different versions of the same thing, but I think we would also
have tools to deal with that. Yeah.
I'm sorry, there's another hand in the back.
Yes. I come to you in a second.
Because Holly's time is over, you can stay up there.
I just want to get all of the speakers of the session to
the podium, then we can start with the discussion part.
And I forgot to say after each of your talks that it was very nice, and
I really liked all of those talks. I'm really happy with the session. Thank you.
Thanks. My last thing I'll say individually,
that was really meant to be a
spark conversation talk, so find me if you want to talk about it.
You don't need to keep looking at mine, but there.
Do you want me to take this off so I can pass it around?
Okay.
No, you can just
use that.
I will walk away from that.
I'll start the discussion with a question for Holly.
Holly, on the very last slide, you had the picture of the fossil,
and there was many little different organisms, probably with different
taxonomic names and those kind of things in that one matrix of
soil. Did you discuss
how you might use regions of interest, like sort of polygons
or spaces around that? And can you say a little bit about how you might be
using that in your digitization workflows?
Yes. So it's a great question. I will also highlight
that one of the biggest challenges we have coming for us is pollen grain
slides because they have thousands of individual pollen grains on a single
slide. So we have to figure that out, because there's no other way.
So sorry, this is a longer answer, but
in paleo collections, we have quite often, a slab with many individuals,
and those are easy because we can do suffixing to the catalog
number for those. But when you get to the slides, we will have to
resolve the regions of interest. We don't have a good way to document that
in our database yet, but it is something that we have to solve.
So if anybody has done that, please let me know.
Sorry, I didn't really answer your question, but acknowledging it's a problem.
I also forgot to say that Frederic is online now, so if you have
questions to Frederic Berger, he will answer from
space.
Okay.
Hello.
There you-- Oh, wow.
Is there any other question for the panel?
Actually, I have a question
to the broad panel. Since most of you are kind of
changing the way collection management is done and
new approaches.
Marie, you mentioned the emphasize, so
getting to understand the position of the collection
managers.
Has there been any resistance from the collection managers to
your individual approaches, or were they
usually on board and see the necessity for change, or is it more like,
"Oh, no. I've always used my old Paradox database.
I'm not going to switch over to a new system"?
That depends very much on the collection managers.
Some managers are
really cooperative and
see the necessity of
sharing data. Others are a little bit more
resistant.
And
also because some collection managers
have worked for a very long time with us and already
switched to new systems, and they really see that as
a burden in their core work. And as I said
They see data management as
not their priority, which makes sense.
And, yeah, I hope I can nudge them in the right
direction, but that's all I can do.
Others want to?
I will say that our collection manager is incredibly supportive of
both myself and Jessica Bird. We bring him ideas and he
says, "This sounds interesting. Prove that you can do it." And then he says,
"Great, go forward with it."
And in general, our entire department is very supportive of us, and they
understand that things need to be modernized, things need to move forward.
Our larger challenge is just ensuring that procedures,
protocols are written down, and that they're able to be followed
properly. So there's always a
never-ending beta test of somebody reading the same sentence and understanding it
differently than somebody else. So there's a lot of training that we go
into with them to make certain that everybody understands the new things that we
are doing.
But overall, they really have been super great and supportive, and
saying, "Yes, please make our lives easier.
Just explain how."
Yes.
I can just do this. Okay.
Similar, for the work that I've been doing, I've
been very integrated with our collections management team, so they've
been part of developing this. And I think that goes a long
way in getting to where we want to go, is making sure they're part of the
discussions, they're part of the decisions,
and they're part of the workflows.
I will say that one of the issues has been that we just didn't have the capacity to
implement a lot of things, so it's going to go a long way that now I have more
people to help. And I think that will help win over anybody else that might still
be a little bit resistant. But that's something that we can't really solve very
easily, so
it's a perk for us right now.
Yeah, I think
working across a broad network, we've seen a lot of challenges
with
individuals that might not be as technically inclined.
So a new system they need to adopt under the pressure of
administrative workloads and stuff have been challenging.
So going in and trying to support that process, and having people
understand why we're doing this. In essence, collection
managers don't own the collections. They are custodians of it.
It belongs to the people. And so we've tried to explain this a lot.
But what we've seen is a lot of people initially say, "Yes, this looks good,"
and then that phases out. It's very important that we continuously
support the development of these things and also the people on the
ground. And so
in many cases, I do a lot of work with understanding how somebody works,
and I try to find that bridge between that
and the system,
so that we initially get them on board with as less friction as possible,
and then gradually phase them into the new system.
That's how we're attempting to do this.
We've had some successes, and we have some resistance and
stuff, but
there's still some time left, so we'll continue fighting the fight.
In our case, I would say I'm not the one who directly works with
the collection managers, but because of our institution, we do
have a
large amount of collection managers with all different feelings
about digitization and changing the collections.
Thankfully, we have lovely people like Nora who have
backgrounds in collections, who can relate to the
collection managers and talk to them about
the process and why it's beneficial to get on board with it.
But of course, there's a little resistance from some.
But I think starting with the people who are interested also
helps them to see the benefits it would have for their collections.
Yeah, maybe two words from me then.
Yes, I work with the collections, and I can only
relate to what you said.
The one thing are good ideas that arise from data
managers, but the other thing is to implement it very well and
to help those who are working with the collections.
And a lot of times, also in the past of our institution, there have
been a lot of ideas, but not a lot of implementation.
So collection managers spend their time helping us, and in the
end, there have not been too many people to really integrate
that into the systems.
But I think now we are on a good way. I talk about this after the
break.
Yeah, just one like to add.
I was also once a data manager, and I developed a bit further, so I
know what you all talking about. But I think what is really
important is to make also the work transparent.
One of our data managers just set up a ticketing board
in our internal infrastructure to see.
So there are tickets
mostly related to data integration into our data management
system. So you see that the data managers are working on that, and you
explain them why it takes longer, why we are faster, and also
publishing the progress. And this is really, really helpful
to make really also the work we as a data management
community are doing visible.
Yeah. I really want to second that.
Given my experience now with two large German institutions,
and the workflows and data management and all the things that we're talking about,
I first want to applaud the organizers to even set up this symposium, because
I think it's so important that this work is made visible,
and for you standing there as representatives for all those people that
work so hard and making this work. And I remember,
Noah, we had conversations years ago.
"Oh, why do we have to write a documentation?
Maybe why do we have to write a guidebook?
Do we really have to publish this? How do we publish this?" And, there
was some debate within the museum whether we need that or not, and it's done now
in the institution. Also, what Sandi is doing, it's great.
That's the way forward for me. But we also have to think about
how do we, as a community, talk to each other about that and learn from
each other? And I think there are basic principles that we can
reuse and use from one institution to the other, although we
are at very different points still in the process.
So, thank you so much, and I really want to see more of that exchange.
And please publish
all the things that you find because I think it is valuable, and it can be
transferred to other institutions.
Thank you.
So I was thinking along similar lines to the last
comment, and I was just curious, in the room, how many
people is your primary role a data manager for
a collection?
Yeah, because I feel like it's kind of a small group, and I wonder if this
conference, and particularly maybe just the panel, but if it would be a good
opportunity to set up some conversations between
meetings like this where we could work on some of that transparency, some of that
data sharing,
even if you can't implement an exact solution that someone else has.
This has been great. These talks have been really relevant to the work that I
do in a way that almost nothing is.
And so I wonder if
we could set something up to continue these between conferences.
I was just going to say,
coming in the next year, TADWIG and SPCH will be having a joint
conference, and that is the number one opportunity to get
collection managers and data people together and
talking together and sharing ideas.
So that'll be June next year. We'll hear more soon.
So you mean we take this symposium along to the next year?
That would be great. Yes. Thank you very much.
Does anybody want to answer to the comment?
Thumbs up. Okay.
Yeah, I think it would be a great idea to start a little data managers support
group.
I'm not sure. Does anyone have an idea for the best way to do that?
Should I write some starter sheet with some email addresses?
Okay, I will.
Does someone else have paper? Because I don't think I have any.
The chat in Hoover.
Okay, the chat in Hoover for this symposium? Okay.
Put your emails in there, and I'll put you all into a group.
Yeah.
I think maybe somebody can help us in forming this interest group
that TADWIG-
It's a different process.
It's a different process. Okay. We start with emails.
I think it
is worth considering about what that could look like, but a couple
conversations to map it out because we'd have to write a document to get that.
What is it? A charter. We'd have to write a charter.
Thank you.
I felt like there's one slight element missing, which is
we talk about the curators and the data managers and the communication between
them. We talked a bit about the bottom-up approach and the empathy.
What's missing is the institutional strategy.
There's so much missing from the data managers being able
to say, "No, this is a strategic direction we're going,"
and "Yes, I know that you feel strongly about what you're doing, but
he's doing that over there, and he's doing that over there." Unless there's a
joint-up effort and a vision as to where the institution wants to go,
there's never going to be that symmetrical dialogue as
to, you should do this, so we can do that, so we can achieve
this. So I do think that part of it is actually getting
institutions involved as well to say, "This is what we want.
This is the future that we see."
Because if not, it becomes a conversation between two groups that don't actually
have the authority to make the decisions anyway, and they're going to have a
fight, and they're going to have disagreements, and yeah.
Yeah. Thank you very much. I think that's the point in the end.
Did I see you? No.
Yes.
Absolutely.
And at Museum für Naturkunde, for example, on the
more higher level, we discussed one of those things in terms of
strategy, talking about collection disclosure as a process
that entails both the physical digital collection,
the digitally born things, everything, and because they
all work according to the same principles in a way.
And so we all can learn from each other in terms of archiving and preservation
that applies to data or to digital assets.
It doesn't really matter. And I think if institutions see that as the new
way forward to communicate, because it's a tool for communication,
that would help a lot. Not talking about, "Oh, we digitized our collection, and we
are that far," but talking about how much did we disclose our
collection according to valuable tools like the MID standard and all these things,
too. They apply to physical and digital collection assets.
So I would just implore that we all kind of try to really stop
separating that because that makes our collections actually less valuable also
in the future.
Thank you.
Does anybody want to add something? Yeah. Okay.
One of the
biggest challenges I've faced in multiple collection management
systems is maintaining current
documentation for the user community.
How do you see the
roles in contributing to the documentation of the
institutional
policies, procedures,
your roles in working technically with the system, with
the collection staff that are actually using the system?
Who do you see as
contributing to development of documentation?
I think it varies a little bit depending on what thing you're
talking about, but everybody has a role to play in documentation.
I like to just repeat to people constantly, "Document
it." And be consistent.
I think
as things evolve, it is hard to keep up with ensuring that our
documentation is up to date
and our practices are up to date, and that's where the consistency piece comes
in. I think as long as we can stay consistent to what we've been doing, then we're
adaptable as things move forward.
It's easier to update both the data and the documentation as we move forward.
I think specifically,
for the things that I was talking about, our team does the initial drafts of
documentation, but then we always incorporate all the stakeholders to
be able to have a say in what the final product looks like,
and it's all versioned. It's never considered a static document.
So we keep it updated as much as we can as the process evolves.
I'm actually going to hijack your question slightly and say that as well
as who should be involved in these conversations, which I agree is
everyone, especially the people that are having to use them daily,
is where are they stored, both short-term and long-term, and
maintaining the one that's the most current and making certain everybody deletes
the old ones off of their computers, and also ensuring that there
is a physical copy of it somewhere and that everybody knows where it's
located.
When we were doing the research for my talk with Chris and inquirers, we
ran into a lot of questions about the data and why things were that we
literally couldn't answer because our predecessors had chucked the old
manuals into the trash.
And so those questions, well, essentially, they're only
hypothesized, right? We have no definitive answer about them.
So I think it's very critically important to whatever system is
chosen to be where they are, that is also written down and widely shared, and is
not just lost institutional knowledge, where somebody new coming in
has to know to ask the question to be told the answer to, right?
So probably part of a
new employee's user
manual, basically, right? Everybody gets one the second they walk in the door and
sit down at the desk.
Yeah. In
amongst the institutions that we work with in South Africa,
similar to what Holly said here, is we provide that initial documentation.
And sort of on the state or sort of ask the room as well back to you
guys here. So we've looked at with the age of AI and stuff,
it's quite easy to generate text. And there's a question about
what is IP that is being generated. So are you writing a paper with it?
Which I'm not fully in support of it.
As a support tool, yes, but not to write the entire paper.
On the other end, what's production, and how do we get information out quickly?
Sometimes when you're working on a system, it's really beneficial to
develop documentation pipelines or
self-documentation of these systems as you are working
in order to make it very easy for people to consume.
And so giving them access to that information in a quick spot also
shortens the time that we can get feedback back from people, where we can then
shape and further develop these things.
So there are some tools to quickly develop documentation for the
community as well that you don't necessarily sell as your intellectual
property. You're very clear about what it does, but it gets the message out.
And so that's helped me, for example, to quickly
get information out to multiple institutions and then deal with the feedback from
that. But like you've also said, this is an
iterative process that is shaped by all stakeholders in our community.
I'm sorry. Thank you for the fruitful discussion, but we have to stop here because
the session is finished now. So I hope you all come back for part two
after the break, and then we can continue talking about this
really important topic. Thank you very much. Thank you.
You're really?
Anybody else?
Ah, okay. Yeah.
No, but you were almost at the end there.
I think in total you had maybe 12 minutes of presentation, but it
was already on this kind of take-home message slide, so I
decided, well,
a reason to
give my
presentation.
And the second one is...
The second one? The second one.
The one.
Yeah. Okay.
It was great. You missed a lot of-
I missed a lot of things because-- Thanks.
You're welcome.
I'll catch up later.
We'll watch the recording.
No, well, I think it was a
bit like about how you manage and how you set up
institutional-
Yes.
-libraries, how to share that, how to integrate
data and all
the challenges-
Yeah.
-all the data managers do
with that.
Yeah.
It was neat
to all come from
different
areas.
Hello?
Hello.
It's
not that one. Do we have our introduction slides available?
The very first. Yeah. Thank you.
Okay. Welcome back, everyone,
to part two of our symposium.
If you were not here for the first half, I will
introduce it again.
This is From Cabinets to Clouds, Bridging the Gap Between
Collection and Database Management, and we are a group from
the Natural History Museum in Berlin,
who work in some parts of the digitization process.
So there's myself, Nora, who you saw earlier, and who
you're about to see presenting,
Frederic Berger, who is online, Mareike Petersen, who is
in the front row, along with Sabine von Mering.
So our idea that we wanted to talk about is
how do physical collections and digital data workflows connect?
We all have different institutions with different workflows
and different teams, different departments who work together.
So who decides what happens, and where do our responsibilities
meet?
We are looking at how we align collection expertise and digital
practices to create high-quality interoperable
biodiversity data.
And we want to learn from each other with what works and what common challenges
we have.
And a key question is how we can build a cohesive workflow from
cabinets to the cloud.
We've already uncovered quite a few of the challenges in the first half of the
session, but I guess we're going to see a few more, and then we will
have a discussion after on
how we can resolve those or what we can learn from each other.
So our first presenter is going to be
Nora Linke-Mass from the Museum für Naturkunde
Berlin,
and she is presenting on Drawers in the Dark: Harboring
Data that Could Spark.
Finding the Sweet Spot in Collection Digitization and Mobilizing
Metadata from Museums' Collections.
Hello.
Okay. I hope you can hear me very well.
Because I don't have pockets, I cannot use the other microphones. I'm really sorry.
As Caitlin said, I'm from the Natural History Museum of Berlin, and I'm
going to take you along in the next couple of minutes to the
digitization process that we faced in the last couple of years.
So I began working in the museum in my professional
career as a digitization manager.
And we could do that because the Museum for Natural History
received a state funding, and we were able to
get this money in order to build up new facilities,
to build up-to-date collection facilities
on-site, and to build a second building,
but also
to digitize our around 30 million
collection objects.
And how did we plan to do that?
Many people thought about that process, and we wanted to
do it in a holistic way. So we want to ensure the proper
conservation of our
objects. 80% of them have still been
stored in historical cabinets, as most of
museums do.
So we wanted to have a look in them, store them properly, then
digitize them in some kind of way and in the end, make
everything accessible to the world.
So,
we had this project, Collection, Discovery and Development.
This group divided
roughly the museum's holdings into four different
categories based on their
traits and composition. So one was the entomology, then the
fossil and the recent vertebrates, mineralogy and geology.
Then the fossil and recent invertebrates, paleobotany, including the
herbarium. This was the field that I was working on.
And then text images and audiovisual media, including
the archive, the animal sound archive, and the library, which
was done by Franziska Schuster. You're going to see her by the end of the session.
And the museum hired four digitization managers, myself and three others,
to push digitization efforts in all of these areas and all of these
collections.
Also, we had hired five scan operators to really
work on the operational
thing of that project, so doing the digitization work on
the objects.
And the project structure had the purpose of
speeding up the digitization, the capture of metadata,
so not only
photographic digitization,
and disclose the areas of interest.
So usually those are the type specimens in each collection, but
also high demanded parts of the collections
which is usually best known by collection managers.
And another purpose was also to prepare the collections
for the move, because since we are doing a new building, every
collection has to move.
And this is the holistic process we thought about.
We wanted to access the condition, as I said, then do a
part of conservation, restoration,
do the inventory, digitization, quality insurance,
until we have a new physical storage for the objects.
And everything in concert,
so user driven, so finding out which parts of the
collection should be digitized first or handled first, and
specific to the object groups that we are digitizing on.
And one of those projects that I did as a
digitization manager, I want to show you now in not too much detail,
but I'm really proud of it, so I wanted to show it to you.
So, I'm a malacologist by training, so it
was fun for me to go first into the malacology because there was always
a trust. We spoke about that in the first part of the session, that there
should be a trust between digitization managers and collection personnel.
So we teamed up with the Fraunhofer Institute for Factory Operation
and
thought about what could be a new innovative way
of digitizing natural history collections.
And then we also had an external partner who helped us out with
the
workflow design and also with personnel to facilitate
this. So this is what malacology looks like, old cabinets,
and it's stored in these little boxes, which are called lots.
There can be one individual inside or many.
So we have roughly 260,000 of that lots in
the malacology, which
translates to about seven million objects.
So we came up with
this station, it's called DORA.
And this is a
fully built digitization station for malacological objects,
but also for objects that have roughly the same traits as
malacological
collections. This is what it looks inside.
So it has four built-in cameras, three of them, so they
are able to focus stack on these
trays. Those are the trays for the objects, and one
camera captures
the label information. Also, this camera is able to
read the QR codes and name those
files automatically.
This is what
the
user interface looks like. So you can see
preview images here, and you can also enter a minimum
dataset for these collection objects.
So in the end, if you scan them, you have really good
high-quality pictures that are focus stacked, that have
a color chart and also a scale and the
identifier in a human-readable way.
Here are the labels, and you
also get a JSON file with all of the information in machine-readable
format as a JSON text file.
So this started in 2022,
this project, and up until now, we were able to
process roughly about 170,000
lots. I have to say, not all of them with the pictures,
but we did the metadata for them and also a big
amount with pictures. So we have been able to
disclose until the 19th
of September, roughly 85% of the collection.
And why do we do not have pictures of all of those objects
is because--
Oh, sorry, I forgot.
Of course, these standardized media and these standardized JSON files
are ready to be integrated into the collection management system as well
as into the media repository. Collection management system and media
repository are
hosted in the digital catalog infrastructure of the
museum, which will also be explained in more detail in the
last talk of this session.
So this is the reason why we couldn't go on with all of the
photographic digitization, because the museum
has been a target to a severe cyber attack in
2023. So everything was laid down
because everything was destroyed in the back end, and we had to
start from zero again. So we have been offline from
October 2023 until July 2024
completely.
But we took this challenge as a starting point to maybe
reorganize and start from scratch, which is not something that we would have
chosen, but it was the way that we kept on
going.
So
we lost also personnel on the way. Of course, funding ran out in
between, so not all of us have been there anymore, and so the
structure couldn't be
moving on like we envisioned it. So now we came up with this kind of
structure in our department, where we built
three different working groups. One working group is the
CoDoDiD working group. It's the coordination office for digitization on demand,
which I lead together with a photograph.
And we are on the way to
facilitate these scannable, reproducible digitization efforts
and workflows. We work together with the DCI team, which I
mentioned before, so the digital catalog infrastructure, who
are responsible to setting up the backbone of this
whole digital
museum's
structure. So here you find the collection management
systems, which is Specify and also the media
repository and the data portal, which will be
online. And then we have another part because
we got third-party funding because of the success
also with DORA and with other stations.
It was envisioned that we have an innovation lab for
digitization infrastructure, and so they are
taking on now the innovation part for digitization.
We are all based on the collections and their objects, their expertise,
their requirements, their research questions, but we are all
working towards an open and integrated research museum.
So just to make a short dip into how we
work in the coordination office, this is the whole workflow.
You don't need to understand in detail.
I just want to point out some
things. Here we have the DoD request
because it was also said in the first session that there are some other
institutions that build on Google Forms.
That is what we did here as well. We have the Microsoft
365 suite, and there is this Google Forms integrated, and
so we did a digitization
request form that can be filled by
in-house personnel.
And
if we move on, here is the
team that serves the request.
We have different specialized stations that can do that.
So from normal focus stacking
stations, we have a station
for draw photography, we have a station for the
archive. We have, of course, DORA station,
EMBA station, and also a
dome where we are able to digitize paleontological
material.
And then in the end, also our process again leads to the
DCI. So we are handing over
formalized
metadata and also media that can be processed
in an automated way
to be integrated into the media
repository and into the collection management systems.
So just briefly for the other two, I
want to show you this one. This is how the
digital catalog infrastructure is envisioned by us.
So I did this
map. So everything is based on the collection management systems
and on, of course, storage in the background.
The media are stored in a media repository and interlinked
via stable identifier via the collection management
system. And
the back end of the data portal
checks on or
The metadata are pushed into the back end of the data portal, and
the back end checks for media in the media repository and everything
together will be at the end,
visible in the front end of the data portal.
For the last, I will go into ELIO. So how do we
do the innovation and how do we keep it on?
This is our Fides station. It's brand new in the museum, and
it was also a
cooperation with a small company.
And
as you notice, it looks somehow familiar to the DORA station,
but it's completely different from the inside.
So here we have consumer cameras that can be
used, and
the operation system is for--
Here, for this station, you can digitize from
different angles, not only from the top, but also from this side.
And this is
necessary to digitize
the entomological collections, which we have a really
high demand.
And this is what it looks like in the end.
Also, we get a scale and pretty nice focus stacked images.
And also here for this station, this has a
network component, and it can-- The standardized
media
are ready to be integrated into GBIF and also in the
future to be integrated in our collection in our digital
infrastructure. The difference to DORA system is that you
cannot capture metadata here. It's just for the media.
So take home messages.
What we learned on the way, plan your digitization efforts for the
easy 95% and not for the problematic 5%,
because you tend to lose yourself into details if you do that.
Collect as many metadata as possible, but try to
settle for the minimal data set to maximize the amount
of specimen you can capture.
We introduced machine-readable aids that avoided mistakes in
naming of media and also naming of metadata
files,
and if possible, combine with different efforts.
So we did try to combine inventory
with digitization or digitization with preparation for the
movements.
Sometimes technological development
spares time in the process, but otherwise, if there's no
development or if you don't have time or money to do that, focus on
the preferably easy solution.
Plan pictures wisely with personnel and time,
and prefer online-based tools than local ones.
We learned it the hard way that everything was lost in between, so I can
encourage you to do that.
And in the end, the museums must decide when perfection slows the
trail and when good enough leads to collection that harbor data
that will spark. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Nora.
I think we have time for one question.
Yes, here.
Hi, first of all, wonderful pictures and beautiful.
I was wondering if you took into consideration to extract DNA while
touching everything.
What, into the collection management systems?
From the insects or anything, wherever possible, to extract a bit of
DNA or subsampling for further research.
To extract from the collection objects?
Yeah.
So we are doing that in a completely different process.
Okay.
We have a DNA bank and
a storage for that. That's going to be integrated in Specify as
well into a different instance for the collection numbers and the
lab numbers. But at that point, we are not so far
to really combine those two, collection and DNA.
Thank you. So if anyone has more questions.
Yes.
So we have a few more. I'll do one more now, and then we have some time for
discussion at the end. So don't worry. Rachel.
Yeah. So thank you very much for the talk and your DORA
station, I'm definitely going to bring back to the museum the idea
of it, not the station itself, of course.
But I have a question about your ELIO. I don't know how to pronounce it.
Yeah, ELIO.
Right.
Yeah.
So you're taking fantastic photos, at least what you showed, right?
So my question is, what do you do with metadata?
What do you do with labels, and how do you connect?
Don't you think it slows down if you cannot do everything at
once? Thanks.
Yeah, it's always a hard question.
This is usually also how the collection managers argue.
It's like if we take it one time, why not do everything?
But in the end, you start to really go into detail research
for individual historical places and names
and stuff like that. And it's cool, I know, but
sometimes you get lost, and that does not really serve the purpose to digitize
everything in the end. So here with the Fides station
that I showed in the end with the ELIO project, their other project that they are
doing is automatic label transcription.
So everything that you put into the Fides station and upload, you have
an AI workflow to grab the
information from those labels. Yeah.
So we're doing both a little bit. Yeah.
Hello?
Hello.
My question is, you mentioned minerals and rocks, and I was just wondering
what the biggest specimens are that you've digitized
and-
How it affects the rate of digitization.
How big, for
the stations or in general?
Yeah. Because you've shown quite small things.
Yes.
And I was just wondering what-- Is there a feedback?
What the largest specimens are that you've photographed, and if you have
any idea how that affects the rate of capturing all the
data.
Bigger objects. So this is what I meant with the 95%
rather than the 5%. So these stations we built in here are
for the 95% of medium-sized
objects. But yeah, we also photographed big elephant
skulls and trace fossils that are two, three
meters huge.
So it slows down a lot. So you have to bring them somewhere,
or you have to bring the photo equipment there to make a proper picture,
find out what is the lighting, engage with the collection managers
to say, "Okay, which one of the views is the most usable for
this kind of object?" So, yeah,
biggest and smallest objects are always the hardest, and it
takes a lot of time to digitize them.
We try to do it on the way.
If there is a digitization request, for example, for
the exhibition department or for other researchers, then we of
course do it, but it's not the first we choose in the digitization
process.
Thank you, Nora.
Thank you.
Okay, next up, we have
Melanie de Leeuw from Naturalis Biodiversity Center,
presenting on accelerating specimen identification
through virtual collections while promoting collaboration.
Hello.
This is very big.
Good morning, everyone. I'm very excited to be here, and I'm also very excited
to share you our work on accelerating specimen
identification through virtual reference collections.
So this is a joint effort between the Tetris project and the DiSSCo
project, both EU-backed projects
that work together with a huge network of different institutions.
So lately, we've been busy turning Discover, our
user-facing platform of DiSSCo,
from a more passive data lookup tool
into a more active, hands-on
workspace. So today, I have the honor of actually showing you
what it looks like and what it does. This is next. Yes.
So natural history collections are the ultimate benchmark, of course, for
biodiversity research. But taxonomy is caught in a bit of
a weird vicious cycle.
So on the first step, we have physical distance that
limits access to remote experts. They simply
can't get to it in time. They have trouble. They have to travel.
So we started digitizing them, and we've been digitizing things
for a very long time, and we're not even done.
We're not even close to done.
And as you could've heard from the different presentations as well,
it takes a lot of work. It takes a lot of effort.
Not everything goes as smoothly as we hope.
So
what we digitize
kind of loses its value if maybe experts still
cannot access them. Because what happens then is that they might be
scattered through different data silos
in institutions, and they're stuck there.
So we sort of get to the first point again that we need experts to actually
physically go somewhere.
So if you take a manager at Naturalis, for instance, with high-res scans
on her drive, but no in-house expert to actually identify them,
her choices are flying someone in,
shipping fragile material, or letting data just sit in a silo.
So to tackle biodiversity loss, we must move from passive image
viewing to a more active remote curation.
So how do we break that loop? Well, we start destroying those
silos. With the DiSSCo infrastructure that
we already have, we try to bring in a lot of collections together on one
platform. We now try to take it a step further by actually
bringing some digital specimen from institutions
together in a nice virtual drawer for experts
to curate them.
That's basically what we do.
That was very short, but so how do they actually work?
Well,
I'm going to show you some screenshots of how it actually looks like.
And we've identified basically three use cases for them.
Quick disclaimer before I dive in.
We're actively ingesting datasets as we speak.
We've been doing that for a couple of years. They're from different institutions.
All the datasets are pretty different also in whether they have
images or not. So these examples that I'm going to show you
are actively curated by me, purposefully
chosen.
I am a software developer and not a taxonomic expert, so if I say
something wrong, please
don't come at me.
The first use case that we identified is curation at a distance.
So take our Sphingidae collection. I practiced that word.
Naturalis holds many hawk moths identified only
to a family level. So we're missing genus, we're missing species name.
A virtual collection with these items pools
together
everything in one view, so remote experts can annotate them
and complete taxonomy without shipping a single box or
moving an inch from their computer.
And because it's powered by Disco or it's built
in Disco, experts get full annotation functionality
right on the digital specimen, turning isolated research into a
more genuine collaboration.
We have use case two, machine learning training data sets.
AI image recognition needs high-quality,
expert-validated data, preferably.
If we use our Pyralidae collection, also
practice didn't really go very well, researchers can
assemble verified specimen sets to train vision
models, ideally. Now, what you're seeing
here is not nearly big enough to actually train a full
model yet, but it is more to illustrate how
maybe a VRC can
tap into already existing digitized collections rather than
waiting for new data to come in. We have so much data.
If we digitize it, we get even more data.
It could be useful.
Then we have use case three,
virtual field guides for taxa that are less known, or
unknown, or very rare. So maybe in paleontology, for
instance, again, just an example, rare fossils are
far too fragile to ship around the world, and reference
material is often scattered across half a dozen European
museums.
So a virtual field guide
could bring those digital specimens into a single digital drawer,
giving field paleontologists or any other expert
an online diagnostic tool without
having to move or call or email and wait for a very long
time.
So what are the key characteristics then of any virtual reference
collection in Disco?
So we identify four pillars.
Persistent identifiers. Every VRC gets its
own PID, which in our case is we assign it a
DOI immediately, making it a permanent,
citable scientific asset. Two,
cross-institutional aggregation.
Pool specimens from Naturalis, from London, Paris, Oslo, all
across Europe, and we put it into one
workspace.
Dynamic entity relationships.
So we add a specimen to a virtual collection.
The digital specimen knows, the virtual collection knows.
They know from each other where they are and which things they belong to.
The user knows. Everyone is happy.
And then the final one, active remote curation.
I already mentioned it a couple of times,
but experts actively validate their data and enrich
metadata from anywhere.
So what does that actually look like?
I wasn't going to challenge any demo gods today, so we have to do it with
the screenshots, but they're reliable. This is what this looks like.
As you can see, we have just a nice overview of the virtual collections
that we currently have. I'm showing you the acceptance environments, even
though everything is live.
But we simply don't have any virtual collections yet in production, so that
was the reason.
They just give you a nice overview of all the virtual collections that we have with
some basic information.
This is fully accessible to anyone. You don't have to be authenticated.
You don't have to be logged in. We want everyone to be able to actually see
this
and do whatever you want with it, basically.
So when you open a virtual collection, you see a few things.
First of all, it actually gets a PID.
Again, this is the sandbox environment, but normally it would get
a DOI.
And you see a title, a description, and basically
the content of what's in a VRC, so all the
digital specimens that are added by the user.
Now, if you want to dive deeper into any individual specimen, just
click on it and Discover brings you straight to all the
data that we have of that specific digital specimen.
You'll be able to annotate it, watch the media of it.
It will all be available to you.
So can you actually create one yourself?
Yes, but
you have to be an authenticated user logged in with ORCID,
and you have to have the right role because we want to hide, or not hide it, but at
least secure it in some way.
But the flow is very simple for now.
So you add a title and a description.
You add all the digital specimen that you actually want to add to the virtual
collection,
and you click on Create Collection.
It's really, wow. It takes five minutes, basically, because
then the back end's going to do things. We don't care about that.
So then what is next?
User group involvement. We've been working with user groups for this
functionality.
And those consist of taxonomy and collection experts
and researchers across multiple disciplines and institutions.
Because functionality like this, or any functionality
actually, can only be built with involvement from our
users because we try to have a user-centric approach,
which I think should be a given.
So next, what we'll also do is we'll add a
functionality to actually modify a virtual collection.
But we keep the stable character in mind.
The final thing,
and more of my DISCO colleagues have already been talking about it,
but we are working on the annotation validation framework.
So we can add an annotation on a digital specimen, we can
modify them, we can delete them.
What about validation, then? That seems to be the most important
part.
So
we're working on it. We're in the framework stage.
Maybe next year. We'll see.
I've been talking a bit
quicker than I thought,
but this is already the end.
If you
have the first QR code, that's actually the sandbox environment.
The second is my LinkedIn.
I want to thank you for your time and attention.
I have
some people to thank, like Wouter, my colleague, for the
functional requirements, Martijn for the wonderful UX design, and
my lovely colleagues for their very
relentless feedback.
Thank you.
Thank you, Melanie. Do we have a question?
Yes.
Well, thanks for this presentation.
My question is, how will you actually handle the
workload, the physical work of updating the taxonomic
identification in your collection once the digital
annotation have been produced online by different
experts?
Oh, that's a very good question.
Thank you.
Honestly, I'm not entirely sure how we would do that, because that would
not necessarily be the technical team,
but it is a very good question that we'd like to also pose with our user groups,
I think, because we're talking with collection managers, and they're
ultimately also going to do the information.
And one of the topics that we've been working on is also how can we
circle the information or the data that we then enrich in
Discover or DISCO back to the actual sources.
So that's part of it. That would be digitally.
But then physically,
very good question. I don't have an answer on that.
I'm going to take that with me to Naturalis.
Okay. Thank you very much.
We can come back to more questions-
Oh.
... in the discussion later.
Oh, are we done?
So, yeah.
Cool.
Thank you. Okay, next up, we have Merian van
Bossem from Naturalis as well, presenting
on managing high volume specimen movements in
the entomological collection of Naturalis with a new type
of record.
This is indeed a big screen. I did not design my
presentation for this screen.
Yes, thank you. We are going back to entomology and
drawers.
I am system owner of the collection management
applications at Naturalis,
and also have a responsibility role of the data
quality.
I will provide some context. I was surprised that not everyone knows
what Naturalis is and where it is located, so I added a picture
of... This is the Netherlands. Leiden is in between The Hague and
Amsterdam,
and we're above Belgium and besides Germany.
This is a drawer of entomology collections.
This is what we're going to be talking about.
And then a picture of our collections tower in
Naturalis.
We have a collection of 45 million specimens,
of which about a third or even more than a third is pinned
specimens, insects,
of which only 10%
is individually digitized, and mostly these are
bees, because bees
can be fuzzy and they're interesting.
The rest has been digitized during a mass
digitization project that was ran 10, 15 years
ago,
but they're only digitized to the
drawer level. So we have a record of this drawer
has these identifications in them, these taxa.
Little bit more context. We have two CMSs currently,
one for botany, which I'm not going to be talking about, and then one for
zoology and geology.
It's created by a Dutch vendor, and it is not designed
for natural history collections, so we, as Naturalis, are the
only users in that context, and we have to write the
requirements to make it ABCD aligned.
We had a problem, or actually, the collection managers came to me with a
problem, and this problem was old,
but they tried it again when I started, and
at some point, there was momentum to actually do something about this.
So their physical problem was that their collection is
taxonomically ordered.
There is a many-to-many relationship between the taxa and the
storage units.
And new acquisitions and taxonomic reclassifications or
reidentifications require shifting physical
specimens across adjacent drawers.
And
the
individually digitized specimens were
not often taken with this in this context. Let's see.
I had a note here.
Then the digital friction was that to reflect
the
physical move, also a digital action was needed.
So the way our records are structured, there is a
storage unit record with a table, you can see that here,
of all the identifications, the taxa that are stored in that
drawer.
If anything was shifted, they had to manually delete from one storage
unit record. First open up that table, find that
identification,
delete it, and re-enter it manually to the
destination storage unit record.
That had impact. People were ignoring this.
It was a lot of work.
Mistakes were being made.
And as I said, the specimens were not moved with them.
So we have a lot of backlog in our systems,
and we have a legal obligation to know where our specimens are,
and that was getting lost.
So we looked at solving a problem.
Our initial approach was to create independent
identification or taxa records attached to
the storage units.
We evaluated that. That was too disruptive to change
the system, the application, the database,
and it was very complex.
So we selected an implementation of what we call the lot record, and
I have already noticed there are several definitions of lots,
and that's also a question for you.
How problematic is this going to be in the future?
Fortunately, we had all those digitized storage unit records.
There was no new digitization involved,
and
we could just do a data
migration
to deal with this.
So our definition is a lot is an
aggregation of specimens belonging to the same
lowest determined taxon physically stored in
one contiguous location. We have one other
complexity that we have several collections
coming together historically, and they are still housed in
separate locations
because their drawer sizes do not match, and it's too much work to
incorporate them physically.
So that means that
a specimen can be linked to exactly one lot.
A lot can be contained in several storage units
because of the contiguous location,
and a storage unit can contain multiple lots.
And one lot has
one taxon, but a taxon can be in multiple lots.
To visualize this, at the bottom, we have a drawer that has a
number,
that contains
this specific lot number with a taxon and 14
more lots.
Then at the top,
you see that lot. It can be across two different
small boxes.
And there are nine others in that storage unit.
Then in the middle, we have an
individually digitized bee.
There are 57 bees in
this lot.
So we
simplified the workflow for collection managers.
Moving a taxon to another drawer
digitally requires only updating the relationship
link of the lot in the record.
It also allows them to
provide the answer on the question, do we have a taxon in our
collection, and where is it located? Where do I have to go to find it physically?
And that result in satisfied collection managers.
One other thing that really made a difference in implementing this is that we
also,
in our taxonomic record, in our identification table,
we have implemented the Catalog of Life API,
which
lessens the amount of data entry errors and
has really helped, and people are very satisfied with that.
What does that do for data mobilization? This is still a work in progress.
Currently, we are still publishing a static
legacy dataset on drawers that was created
eight-plus years ago on GBIF.
So we need to do work on getting that to
a
live dataset on these lots.
But how do we map to Darwin Core Archive or Darwin Core Data Package?
That is a question to be answered. That's why we have not done this yet.
And this is a question for you as an audience, especially because I've seen
other work on storage units and different definitions of lots.
Is there a use case for these types of records
on Discover or DBif, for example?
And that was my presentation. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Do we have questions for Miriam?
Okay. Well, thank you very much. Maybe if something pops up, we
can discuss it in the whole group later.
Okay. Then our last presentation for this time
slot is Franziska Schuster and Jasper
Funk Smid from the Museum für Naturkunde Berlin, and
they are presenting "Everything is Coded: How to Present a Game of
Telephone in a System Full of Interfaces."
Hi. Does it work? Yes. I feel I would
rather sing the presentation like in a musical, but maybe I
wouldn't. Okay. My name is Franziska Schuster.
I'm at the MfN in Berlin, responsible for the
development of the digital collection, and we are two of us here, but I will hand
over to Jasper later.
We have seen that before in Nora's presentation.
So what we see here is our digital catalog
infrastructure overview, the way we present it to our
non-technical stakeholders.
This is, at the MfN, the very prerequisite for
being, at some point, able to link our digital
collection to
global knowledge repositories.
So it's kind of our homework.
Today, we don't want to talk about the technical modules of this
infrastructure, but we want to have a look at the
human-to-human relationships that goes beyond the
boundaries of
different professional backgrounds, which happens during all these little arrows
that we can see here.
Before I hand over to Jasper, who will present an example
of this human-to-human relationship, I'm going
to emphasize a little on the metaphor we had in our
talk title. Oh, where I'm now. This is back the last one.
Okay, this is the beginning.
Here we are,
which is the game of telephone. When I was a kid, I
loved this game. So you whisper a phrase to your neighbor's ear, and
that goes on and on until, in the end, the phrase is very different from what you
said at the beginning. And it's really funny when you play it as a game, but
in reality, we don't really want this.
We prefer that the meaning of a message
remains untouched from the beginning of a communication chain
until the end. But
I'm a media scientist by training.
That's why I know very well that person's professional
background and emotions, expectations, and
experience has a lot of influence on how you
receive the content of a message.
So
to prevent that, that the meaning is changed during
communication, we are using coded systems
that narrow down the definition of terms, like in mathematics, for
example.
But this only works when both parties, like the
sender and the receiver, have an idea how to use this code.
So what we're talking about is, of course, standardized data formats
like Darwin Core Archive, which we also use within the digital catalog
infrastructure.
But we want to argue that this alone is not
sufficient to make sure that the meaning of the data is preserved
throughout the whole process.
And this is where I hand over to Jasper to present the sample.
Yeah. Okay.
Hello,
I am Jasper. I work as a developer at the MfN, and
I'm going to focus on a small
problem in a large data set. So we had a project
at the MfN called Digitize. This was about
a Pictory-developed conveyor belt pipeline for
digitizing a part of our
insect collections,
which worked very well.
600,000 specimens, a bit more, I think, were
digitized with over two and a half million
images. The labels were photographed separately.
Yes. And so we had these records. We had them in a
management system. Then unfortunately, the museum got hacked, as
was mentioned by my colleague.
And we had
many panicky efforts to rescue all kinds of data,
making backups here and there, and in the end, we had an
offline management system and a fragmented data
set. Okay.
Since the
VMS for our specimens is Specify,
the purpose of this exercise was, of course, to get all
this information into Specify. And since we've been
working on restoring our systems for a long time now,
this data set landed on my table about
three, four months ago.
So
this was a machine-made data set, so all the
fields were
identical, well-defined,
and
Specify had specific requirements, so everything looked
very nice and easy, and we can just
process the files and map it to
Specify. Okay.
The first
period was to resolve the initial fragmentation, identify
duplicates, getting everything into one single storage.
That took some time, but it was
done.
Then
I got to
writing the mapping code for Specify.
In my assumption, this was a simple process, so I wrote a simple iteration
with Python and mapped all the fields, had
feedback from
Specify and from the collection managers, and they said, "Oh,
yes, this is very interesting, but there is something missing." Okay, well, we can
add it. We'll add the missing parts, and I send it
back again. I get more feedback, and
slowly this
feedback loop of requirements, what Specify required in
relationship to our dataset,
got more and more complex. By the end, I was slowly iterating
over 600,000 JSON
files, and every iteration
made my code slower and also made it harder to check what my output
was. So I was losing control over my own
code, and I could not really identify anymore, at some
point, if the changes I made actually made sense, if this
was actually readable. And a main part of that was, of course,
that
the requirements of Specify,
the input of the datasets, they were not clear for me in
the beginning.
Okay. So
I
already
published about
22,000 records to
Specify, but it was not a workable situation anymore, so I had to take
a month to rewrite it.
So
now I will focus on a very particular problem inside this
dataset,
which is taxonomic identifiers.
In the Museum of Natuurkunde, the ghost of
NURIs has been going around for quite some time.
And a NURI is a Natuurkunde Unique Resource
Identifier, or Natuurkundemuseum, probably. I'm not even 100% sure.
So anyway, there's been a lot of talk about NURIs, what they are, how to
implement it, how we're going to use them.
And in essence, a NURI can be used for anything to
a specimen, a drawer, a taxonomic entity, a media
item. It is a simple random ID that we can
use internally.
Which is fine,
but in my dataset,
I discovered, because I had to prepare,
I was exporting the taxonomic information
together with the taxon NURI that was assigned.
But what I discovered was that a lot of taxon
NURIs were not referencing unique taxonomic
concepts. So
I had
sometimes entries with up to 2,000 supposedly
unique identifiers for a single taxonomic entity.
I had empty taxonomies that had an
identifier. I had entries that say, which was my favorite,
"123abc: This is a test."
And okay. And
once again, I iterate these things, and I give feedback to the
Specify managers, to the collection managers, and we ping-pong this back
and forth. And then at some point, we come to the point that
we also used drawer
identifications as taxon identifications, which, as
my predecessor already discussed, is not necessarily a one-to-one
relationship. So more and more problems
appeared.
Yes. How was that solved?
Okay. In
the end, the problem is manyfold actually, because
the people involved in the digitization process are either
not there anymore or have different interpretations on how it
was implemented. So it was very hard to reconstruct
which data is supposed to reference that.
And worse, is it's very hard to reconstruct
if a specifically used taxonomic identifier is
out there in the world. Because if it's out there in the world, we cannot simply
throw it away.
But we don't know. We don't know. Partially because of the hack, partially
because the documentation on this process was
extremely
nonexistent. And I basically had to dig
into the history of the project and all
individuals involved that were still there to be able to
get a moderately sensible reconstruction of the
problem.
In the end, what I did is I take a unique
taxon. If there is only one and only one
taxon NURI, I'm going to assume it's correct.
If there's multiple, I'm going to ignore it from the taxon tree
and put it into the determination object to
preserve findability in the rerun.
Yes, this is what's meant with spamming the comments field.
So what went wrong?
A great many things went wrong, obviously, as you can hear.
I think
many people within the digitization process
had
different understandings of what the taxonomic NURI is.
And I think this was also enhanced by
a certain lack of acceptance of the idea of
using this concept. So
this is something that really supports
the development of problems.
Then there were
on-the-fly decisions to use drawer NOIDIs
as taxon NOIDIs, which made no sense from a logical perspective.
But
due to time pressure and due to stress, we want to do
as much as possible. Somebody somewhere has decided, "Oh,
let's do it like that, then at least we have some reference." Which is fine,
but now it's my problem.
And I think one of the key questions that was not
sufficiently asked in the beginning when
assigning taxonomic NOIDIs is,
is the data we have at this point in time
actually sufficient
to assign an identifier?
Is this actually the time to do this?
Because it would have made more sense, and it would have been really nice if I
could have just pumped it all to Specify and
make identifiers then, because then I have my tree, I have my unique
entities, I can assign identifiers.
Why this has not happened, I
have tried to discover, but I could not, unfortunately, discover that.
Yes. So this is the end of my part, and I added
some bonus tips. Don't get hacked, and use a database
from the get-go. That's it.
Oh, no, there's more coming, I think.
Yeah, just to wrap it up a little bit.
What we heard is a very good example for this game of telephone effect that we
don't really want to have, because when we handed over the information from the
collection management level to pipeline engineering,
there was a lot of misunderstanding.
So we heard it's really important to make clear at the beginning of the
design of the process that we have a common understanding of the
meaning of the data, which is also very important because the collection management
has to trust this infrastructure because they have to give away their
data and kind of lose some of their control over it.
And when things like that happen, this is
destroying the trust more or less.
So,
I think we're close to running out of time.
I just wanted to say we were very much looking
for a project management system that would help us to
avoid to panic, because when we just look at this example, we
see it's just a tiny bit of one pipeline from one
subcollection and from one group of insects.
And when we then have this big
system with a lot of errors, we can just get overwhelmed by how, my God,
how should we get done with this whole infrastructure?
And that's why we chose an agile approach, and I won't
go into detail to explain what it is.
If anyone is interested in Scrum, there's a lot of very good videos on
YouTube to watch about that.
Two things are important for us.
One is that
the process of translating this big and scary vision
into manageable and understandable development tasks is
an ongoing process inside Scrum, because we are working
iteratively.
That means we have sprints from three weeks and
after each sprint, and this is the second important thing
about Scrum, is that we always get in touch directly with the stakeholders
so that we can get direct feedback to a feature that we
developed,
and then adapt our strategy so that things like with the
dataset we have seen do not happen, so that we can always adapt the design.
Yeah, and in the end, this is just trying to have a
"don't panic" strategy for the whole team, which works quite well.
And,
yeah, so this is what we wanted to present today.
We're very happy
if you have some questions for us or get in touch with us later.
Yeah.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank
you.
Questions.
Yes.
I guess I wanted to say that I identify very strongly with
your talk because this is a situation for data managers that
happens all the time.
I think my biggest issue is when I say, "This is important.
This is very important. Don't drop this number."
It gets translated into, "This is a number.
Isn't this nice?" And then it gets translated to, "Oh, well,
I didn't use that number." So then there's no link back to the actual
original record.
And I don't know if that may be part of the issues, or I was wondering,
because we're using the same conveyor system now at Smithsonian, do you
think a lot of the issues were just a lack of
beginning preparation for the project? Just curious.
I think you can answer that.
It's hard to say.
If I listen to the people involved, there was actually
a lot of thought
put into it in the preparation phase.
It's just that the
implementation was not
solidly
... thought through and that there were creative solutions on the
run.
But
I think also a part of it is that there's a
higher level strategic decision to push for a certain
development, which is not quite
understood at all levels. And then you get a
wishy-washy,
half-baked solution that people don't actually understand what they're
doing or why they're doing it. And I think this is a
large source of error.
I'm not sure if I answered your question.
Okay.
Also, at that time, we didn't have our collection management system running, so we
couldn't feed the data directly into it.
So that would have been
easier to have the mapping just at the beginning of the process, which we are
now doing retrospectively.
Should I?
So I have two questions,
and my second question
is just a loud question, but I will start with the smaller question.
So you digitize, correct me if I'm wrong,
600,000 specimens, right?
Can you tell me how long did it take?
And my second question, if I can just continue.
Just to try to see a positive side from
the cyber attack. I'm not a hacker, I didn't attack you, but still,
a cyber attack.
Did that somewhat help you
to move into one proper data
management system?
Yes.
I think it did.
The decision to do it was around earlier, but what
we decided after the attack was that we would choose a
cloud-based approach so that we would not host it
ourselves, which is why we got into a closer relationship with the
Specify consortium, which is of course helping a lot to
make it happen. So yeah, this was the side effect of the
attack.
Sorry, I can't hear you.
So that was a little bit of a push, right?
Yes.
Nora also mentioned that
we had to rethink our whole infrastructure, and when you have a
grown system where you have, maybe you know this big ball of mud
metaphor, where you just add things.
If everything is gone, you can rethink things.
But sometimes you have the problem of over-engineering
or something, so starting from scratch is not always good,
but it is a chance.
We also had a quick question.
What was the first question?
Yeah.
I didn't really acoustically get it.
How quickly did we digitize these 600,000 objects?
How long? How long did it take? Or you need to help us.
How long did it take?
Two years, or how long was the pipeline?
I think it's a bit tricky because together with Pictory, we
developed that together, so it was not ready to get
started. So there was a lot of testing phase and so on and so forth.
So I think it was in total two and a half years, maybe.
Yeah.
Okay, I would invite all of our-
5,000 specimen per day.
Thank you.
I would invite all of our speakers back up onto the stage, and we can open a
discussion.
Does anyone have any questions to start us off, or
comments or learnings, takeaways?
Just a short comment. So my colleague, Frederick Berger, he's online
available, so if you have more questions regarding the Pictory
workflow and data things, just reach out to him.
Yes, thank you all for excellent presentations.
This connects a bit with the
question Miriam posed.
Should lot numbers or drawer numbers be provided to
infrastructures GBIF and Disco?
In my head, I always have a distinction between asset information, so things
to look where is it exactly in my collection, and kind of
metadata on who found it, who was the collector, when was it collected.
And
the second part I would imagine to go out, but is there asset
information which is actually really important to get out of there,
and reasons why you would like to include storage units
or lot numbers in there?
To whom was the question?
Sorry.
Is this on?
Yeah.
Okay. So
what we see from collection side
is that
researchers want to know whether we have a specific
taxon in the collection.
And by
providing those lot or storage unit
records
to Discover or GBIF, they can see we actually have that in the collections,
and then they can contact us,
see how many we have available,
from which places, and if they are interested in that.
So from a researcher perspective or the questions
that our collection managers get from researchers, that is valuable
information.
It would be better to have individually digitized objects,
knowing when exactly were they collected, from which
locality, by whom, but we don't have
that yet. But the most important question is:
do we have this taxon in the collection?
And for the collection manager, then the next question is: where is it
located?
And by this solution, we can do that.
We don't
have to provide the details of where is it stored
in to Discover or GBIF.
That's something for collection managers only.
Also,
the definition of the lot and the lot number is really different.
That's what you said, because I
was in the malacology a lot, and so the lot number
there is the collection number. And so there are many individuals
inside, and this is the manageable unit in that collection.
So of course, you share this.
And now we started,
if you are digitizing individual specimens from this lot, they
get a machine-readable identifier, which is related
to the lot then.
But in malacology, usually it's not possible to digitize the
individuals all on that individual level.
I wondered if NFM can describe the scrum process, because I
was a little confused how that applied to your solutions.
Yeah, it's very hard to understand the questions.
So when I go into the whole scrum process, that will take some
time, but
to make it short, it's an agile process where you
operate with a backlog, which you prioritize.
So we put everything that is required for the product that we
develop into the backlog and put a label to it, like must,
should, could, and won't, which is for me the most important
because that means this is out of scope.
But nevertheless, it remains in the backlog so that we can see what we are
not going to do. And then we go over this backlog again and again, and prioritize,
put the things that we are going to develop next up, and
then we translate them into these chunks that are
developable. So you have a lot of things that
you take into your sprint, and you only focus on those things for the
next three weeks. And then you have one feature developed, which you
present, get feedback, and then you go over this again.
And that's the way it circles all around all the time.
And this comes from software development, but we could really well adapt
that to our process.
Okay. Any more questions from the audience?
Did anyone learn anything that stood out to them that they're going to
take back to their institutions, or more questions for their
institutions, or...
Hopefully that's a yes.
Well, thank you, everyone, for coming and presenting and
staying with us for the last few hours.
Give another round of applause to our presenters.
Thank you.
And just a reminder, if you want to join a data manager's
email group, you can send me your email address
on Whova
or give it to me.
I just got reminded earlier from the TED Week
committee that you should sign up for unconference topics
in the Whova app. So please do that if you have something to
share there. Thank you.
My name is Ye Lee from the Korea National University of the
Heritage. Today
Mm-hmm.
Are you having a talk or just-
No, it's for questions.
It was a discussion.
It will probably be not used so much now. Just in case.
I think leave it on and you- No, you can turn it on and off.
It's fine. Oh, okay.
I keep that channel on, so-
Okay
... you're online.
Fine.
When you're online.
Okay.
Am I live? Yes, I am. Always hard to be the guy who comes
after lunch because everybody slowly puts their heads down.
Hopefully, you got enough coffee. There was coffee. I had some. Can you tell?
So welcome to our session.
I have to remember what our session is. Oh, yes. Right.
If you are here, this is Symposium 42,
entitled Solutions for Research Collection Management System Challenges.
So we're going to have a number of speakers come up talking about different
aspects of this. But I think the key point here, and
you may notice our use of the word research.
So we talk a lot about collection management systems.
There are many talks here, throughout the time.
But, one of the things that I've noticed as a researcher and as someone who
leads big projects across multiple different researchers
is
the ability for researchers to manage their data in their
spaces and trying to
maintain consistency, get them to follow standards,
think about interoperability.
They want to do data integration.
We need to figure out ways, they need to learn how to
integrate and how their practices actually allow other
people to integrate data together, and how their
practices may need some help.
Of course, we're always evolving, and we're going to see that in several
talks here. We have different systems that highlight different
ways of doing things, but in the end, it really is about
getting data into standardized formats that are as fair as
possible, and therefore, when we go to the large challenge
of data integration, we know we have a fighting
chance.
So,
I think that's all I'm going to say.
We will have a discussion
following all of the talks. That will be in the second session, so
after the break. This has two sessions, in case you didn't know.
And
we have, I think, only two virtual talks, so most of the speakers are
here.
And
if it goes like most of the other sessions have gone,
most people will fill their entire time allocation.
And so we will likely leave most questions to that
discussion period,
just so you know.
Jonas, did I forget anything?
All right.
So,
moving on past the introduction, our first speaker
needs no introduction, but anyway,
please come up, John. It's John Maschke.
He's going to talk about "From Specimens to Networks: Darwin Core Data
Packages in Practice."
Thank you, James.
Sounds like this is on already. I hear myself echoing back.
I'm one of those virtual presentations,
even though I'm here. I didn't get enough sleep last night.
Let's see if I can run this. Next and back.
I think I can do that. First, I want to give a preface that this
is 10 minutes. I hope you didn't come here
thinking that you could leave here being able to map
your collection management system to a Darwin Core data package when you walk out
that door. Ten minutes isn't enough.
My other hope is that at least you can
get some feeling for what's possible.
So, with that, I'll jump into the first
level of things. Up till now, Darwin Core has been a bag of
terms. That's the term we have used to describe
that really it was a bunch of classes and properties and a couple of controlled
vocabularies to help us have the same language when we talk
about, for example, a catalog number.
When I say catalog number, it means the same thing as what you mean
when you say that. Here, a conceptual model is a different
layer. It's the first time that we have
contributed as part of the standard, which this is now,
a layer of semantics at the level of
the classes in Darwin Core. Every box on here is a
Darwin Core class. And so what we're talking about here
are relationships between higher-level concepts.
And this is a first. I'm not going to go into the full details of
this model because we're only here talking about or
focusing on one part of that, which is sort of hidden in the middle there, the
material entity.
So, in Darwin Core, this is what a material entity is.
An entity that can be identified, exists for some time, and
consists in whole or in part
of physical matter while it exists.
So, that should be straightforward.
It's non-controversial, but it doesn't say much about how to
use it. And there are some examples that go along with this,
but I wanted to actually take an excerpt below
from the conceptual model document
that describes a little bit more in detail how material
entity fits into a bigger picture.
So, here it says, "It may consist of, for example, an entire
organism,"
where I have that capitalized and in italics on purpose because it's a Darwin
Core organism, "a part of an organism,
a member of an organism, or non-biological material, or
even environmental samples."
So, that's the definition of the concept that we're
starting with.
Most of you would think of that as a specimen.
So, if I look only at the part of the conceptual model around
the material entity itself, it already has a relationship.
This relationship is self-referential.
It means that one material entity can reference another.
And if you look at the labels below that
relationship, you see that there are actually two of them.
What that means is that there are two self-referential
relationships for material. One is, "I am part
of something bigger"
and is part of relationship, and the other is, "I was taken
from and I'm no longer physically connected with
something else."
So, derived from relationship, and both of those exist in the model,
both conceptually and in practice in Darwin Core data package.
If we want to start to put this in a bigger context, then
material entities, most of us are used to collecting
things in the field and having
an event and a location, a time and place, context
in which that happened.
But that's not the only thing that material entities can engage in
event-wise. One is we go out and collect it.
Another is actually being sampled from something else, and that
might be in the field or it might be in the lab.
So, we're not talking only about collections and occurrences here.
We're talking about all the things that material can engage in, all the things
that it could participate in. And then the third one is what I described before.
You can actually have events that describe the processes that derive
one material from another.
So, lab procedures.
Then we put it into yet a bigger picture, the one that we started with in our world
when we created Darwin Core and ABCD, which is to try and
understand all of our collection material in the context
of what it means in the bigger world and where
organisms occur. So, here we're connecting it to occurrences
and to the identifications of those things or determinations of those things
to some taxon or taxonomic concept.
So, an identification fits into the model as being
of a material entity, a specimen, or
based on a material specimen as the evidence for an occurrence.
Go one step further, and now we're talking about more
complex contexts. Here, I am
presenting that the location might be
complicated
by
the context not being contemporary.
So I might have a fossil, and the
stratigraphy in which that fossil was found is,
in some ways, an attribute of the location in which I found it,
but it gives me more information.
And what it does is it separates, which is why I have two events, it
separates the act or event of collecting
today
from the occurrence that that implies or infers
far in the past.
So my geological context can provide me with one event that is different
from the one that I went out and collected, and that gives me the
possibility to describe occurrences faithfully and my collecting event
faithfully. And then the same exact thing can apply not
just for geological things, but also for
those events that are dated by chronometric
processes. Chronometric age
is the class for that, so things like
zooarchaeological specimens
and so on.
So that puts us in a much bigger context.
Now, that's to say nothing. I don't even have room on the slide
anymore for words, because I'm bringing into it how
material entities might play into the bigger picture with
molecular data. So I don't want to go into a lot of detail on the molecular
stuff, but basically what we're able to support is the persistence
of a material entity or a used-up material entity that
we no longer have, as the basis
for a nucleotide analysis
following some molecular protocol, providing us with
sequences in one case, or for example,
having a sequence that we're trying to match against and say, "Yes, we've
got it." So metabarcoding or targeted DNA types of
analyses, with or without any material remaining.
The thing is, what we want is that connection of the original material to an
event where it was collected to provide us with an inferred
occurrence, because the event tells us where and when,
and the rest tells us
what
taxon that was.
So that puts us into the much bigger picture.
And then we have the details around the edges.
So the conceptual model, and indeed, the Darwin Core data package,
allow us to
do add-ons, and the add-ons are in all of these
different categories. The material entity is just one
thing that all of these other boxes might attach to.
You can do the same thing with events. You can do the same thing with media.
Basically, what you're seeing on the screen besides material entity gets multiplied
by all the different boxes on my first slide.
That's why I only show it once.
But basically, on the bottom here, we have the classes in
Darwin Core that we're interested in connecting to material.
So people, those are the agents.
People in institutions or
software, AI, all those things can be agents.
They have the capacity to act. And how do they get related to, for example,
a material entity? Through up in the upper middle, the
material agent role.
So I can have a table of distinct agents, me and my
AI. Those are the two things in my agent table. But we can do lots of things.
I, at least, can go out and collect.
My AI agent can
do some kind of a determination off of a media item, or it
can--
Well, sufficient.
I can have a table of media, and those media might contain multiple
things. It might contain a picture of a specimen, or it might contain a picture
of an organism in the wild with
background information about habitat.
So it's actually got more than one thing in it, and I want to be able
to relate that. So that's why I have a material media
table that allows me to tell you that this media is about that material,
but I can also have an
event media table that talks about the stuff that's not directly
related to this media, and so on and so forth through
references, provenance, usage policies, protocols.
And then on the left, the material assertions are our equivalent of
measurements or facts.
We can define all of them that we want to.
It's scalable, and we can also apply all the identifiers we
want in the world to a material entity.
So those are the adornments
that the data package and the conceptual model
allow you. Here, I'm switching to just
quickly introduce in three slides a tool that will help you to
understand and play with
the Darwin Core data package in function of what it is that
you think you have. So I've got some check marks over there about
three tables that I know I'm going to need.
I know I'm going to need an event, an identification, and material.
I actually chose some more of these, and then I have the
option to look at that in
a network model. So this is some
other slide that I gave you earlier,
given to you, built for you through this tool, the Darwin Core
Data Package Designer, and it shows all the relationships, and
things are clickable. You can find definitions.
You can understand what evidence for means.
It's defined, et cetera, in this tool.
And then finally, once you think you've got everything you need
selected, then it can generate for you a data package
.JSON file, which describes what you expect to be in
your CSV tables when you build the package that you're going to send
to somebody.
So, obviously, 10 minutes, I can't Do one for you.
But the important thing here is that link in the bottom so that you can
play and understand if you're able to map your
data into something like that.
Thank you.
And I will invite Matt Yoder to the stage.
Matt's going to talk about aligning an evolving global data model to
software with global ambitions, GBIF
versus TaxonWorks.
Am I on?
Mic check. Mic check, mic. There we go.
All right, thanks.
I'm going to start with a poll,
just to get some audience interaction.
Who has heard of TaxonWorks here? Show of hands.
Okay, warms my heart. Who has contributed to the new TDWG
Data Package standard beyond John?
Also a good number of people, great.
And who is using the new TDWG Data Package standard, like actually
applying it?
Okay, so we got a couple few. Very cool.
So it's emerging.
Let me see here. There we go.
So a quick introduction to TaxonWorks.
TaxonWorks is a bit of a software. It's a workbench.
Its
goal is to find a balance, balancing strict semantics
with flexible extensions.
We're looking at recording data from the past, collections, and the future, sort of
that field work.
We serve taxonomists first, but then we became useful for collections, so there's
now 10 or 11 collections that are quite large, including some virtual collections
that are managed in TaxonWorks.
We like to think that we're approachable software, that we're API first.
So we're one of the first platforms where we have an API, application programming
interface, to all of the models in the system, not just the UI.
We have things like unit tests that help our code expand and
help us use agentic models.
You can use the TaxonWorks data model in a headless way, sort of as a data
conversion process.
It's configured so that both humans and
agents can contribute to the code base in a nice way.
And so we have this relationship with standards where we are both influenced by
standards, the TDWG standards, some OWL standards, a lot of the applications, and
we both sort of influence standards, right?
But we don't try to be completely constrained by those standards.
And so,
this new standard, this DP package came out, and I was like, "Oh, great."
We have Darwin Core import and export in TaxonWorks, and it's getting fairly
mature. It's sort of this mature at middle-age stage.
We have fixed IPT that's built-in, so you can serve by a single endpoint
right to GBIF in there. It has a metadata persistence so
that you can store your EML files there.
Extensions media, we can serve on-demand faceted
slices of data that are in Darwin Core format.
Import-wise, we can have lossless import to
TaxonWorks native fields from Darwin Core fields, so those are lossless ones.
We can also map to TaxonWorks native fields that aren't in Darwin
Core, and you can create your own data attributes that you want to be able to
import. And we're using this importer, it's a UI and also in code,
to handle hundreds of thousands of specimens.
This recent Orthoptera project downloaded over a million
specimens from GBIF, vetted them, served them back in, including
800,000 iNaturalist things. So great, we have all this done and
now boom, new format. Gee, thanks John and TDWG and
GBIF. We have to think about it. So the rest of the talk, I'm just going to be
conceptual like John and align the work that was
all here. I will say this is awesome.
This was a very fun exercise for me, thanks to how John and
TDWG set it up. You can go and see all of those concepts that John alluded to here.
And if you want to see the concepts, because we are very much aligned,
of TaxonWorks, you can come to docs.taxonworks.org and find on through
there.
So too long, didn't read the whole rest of the talk.
If you want to take it,
the final message is that
the overlap of the concepts in TaxonWorks and how we thought of it
conceptually with DP is uncanny,
and this has been in play for seven, eight, nine years.
So here are all those concepts that John mentioned on the side in these two
columns, and this is what we call them, right? The names don't define the thing.
There's a concept behind them. These are the concepts that you would find
them under TaxonWorks.
And you see that there's a couple of things like survey that aren't in TaxonWorks,
that we need to. And there's a couple of things that we'll get on and talk
about how they overlap in sort of an interesting way.
And there's a couple of things that we've planned, but we just haven't built.
But conceptually, the overlap is remarkable, okay?
And this is in a working tool.
John mentioned the one kind of data here, the special kind
of relationship. I can't remember the word he used, but we call that same
relationship an annotation class.
So here, the media relationship to all of those different things, just like John
explained, is exploded out into these four, one, two, three,
four, five, six concepts, right? You can apply media to everything.
So we use that same conceptual pattern in multiple ways in TaxonWorks, and we
think of that relationship as a depiction.
So one image can depict many concepts in the database.
And we do this not only for images but for many different things.
So
identifiers, we can stack as many as we want, protocols, references,
attribution, usage policies. This one sort of
relationship that has an ID in your database, and then the class, the
concept name is also in here. So all of these tables in DP
collapse to one table in TaxonWorks.
So application implementation-wise, this is nice.
There's no better way to do this, is the take-home way.
They both represent data in
the same way. But there's some advantages to one side or the other in
specific use cases.
Now, one of the interesting things I found in this comparison exercise is that I
didn't get bogged down in taxon names and taxon concepts.
And I think that's an interesting evolution of how Tadbank has evolved, and I was
very grateful for that. This is nicely compartmentalized and
encapsulated without reference to that.
So when we're making all of those kind of conversations, we can then think about
how are they related? Because they're not all one-to-one.
We don't have DP as a native data format in TaxonWorks.
We have related concepts. So the SKA thing says things
like concepts are broader or narrower than
each other. And so for example, we can say that the DP agent is broader
than TaxonWorks people. Same idea, but we don't have that
machine part of it. So we have a broader than relationship from TP.
And just quickly,
the annotation layer, the DWC annotation, those
are all the exploded ones, is narrower than the different kinds of
TaxonWorks annotations that we can do. So you saw about five there.
We may have eight or nine different kinds of annotations that we can do there.
And I don't have the time to go through them, but you can see that the semantics
are now evolving as we have a map. We have a way to map a subject, a
relationship, broader than, narrower than, to
an object.
John was talking earlier about what's in one that's not in the other.
And so this is that sort of Venn diagram.
In TaxonWorks, we are missing this concept of this survey, this primacy of it.
It's going to be really important, and I'll say a little bit more.
We use event much narrower, but it's really just the subclass of the concept in
DP.
And we don't have this full concept of a full analysis.
We would call it a granularity.
DP is missing a couple of things as well, and this is just some highlights.
And I don't know which of these are actually going to be important to think about.
One of them is that we have more granularity. We have precision anatomy.
So when John talked about a material entity that is part of some
organism, we can link that to an anatomy ontology directly.
It's the same relationship, we just have a bit more precision there.
We have things like physical containers.
There were some wonderful ideas about tracking collection management attributes and
projecting out to that. So we have a nested hierarchy of physical containers that
you could model your collection in, et cetera.
And some other interesting questions.
We have a bit more primacy for geo-references, loans, things.
These are just some of the highlights that might be of interest. Thanks.
Five minutes. All right. So when we've done that pondering, how do we
persist it? Well, there's this emerging standard called SSSOM, and it has
many different reasons. And that lets us capture that mapping from
subject to predicate. So we can imagine storing all of our
mappings of TaxonWorks data model to
the DP model in this SSSOM format. And then
really interesting conceptually, we could think about taking everybody's
application, all of their mappings, and we could merge all those in an RDF
format. And now, if you're familiar with the OWL world, they have an ontology of
all ontologies called Uberon. But we could have a data mapping of all data mapping.
So it's really cool concept. The other thing that was really nice is I could
come to that endpoint, and I could see that vocab terms right there.
And so there's this concept. What if we all had in our applications a /vocab,
and I could quickly go into your web app, and I could just go, "Okay, I know it's
the community. They've got a /vocab endpoint," and now I can start
reading about what the concepts are in that term.
Zooming along, both
models have buckets for fuzziness.
We don't model everything, but we give you ways to extend things.
And I find it interesting that the DP version of that is traditionally
been this resource relationship.
That's where you mapped everything else if you didn't have a model for it in the
extension. Now you have this new assertion that you heard John reference.
So you have two buckets, and there's going to be a bit of confusion as to which
bucket it goes into. In TaxonWorks, we have exactly the same thing.
We can capture observations, which are the assertions on any class of
concept in the system. But we have these buckets. So why did this come to be?
Has something to do with the nature of how we build applications and need these
little spots to slot data.
But this causes some problems that we need to anticipate, but at least we can be
aware of it.
If you give users multiple ways to do the same thing, they're going to get
confused, and they're going to want the better way of doing it.
So some hints about what we might do.
So two last slides, some considerations.
One of the things that struck me is that Darwin Core was promoted as
the archive was an exchange format.
But what's DWC-DP? Because if
you're mapping your system to this much more
rich model, is that intended to be an exchange format?
Because for us in TaxonWorks, it's going to be not so bad.
But instead of mapping everything into one exchange format, I have to map
50 models to 40 models. So application-wise, there's more
going on there.
In both worlds, comments are being
used as definitions, and so there is some confusion when I read the comments of
DP and I read the comments in TaxonWorks code,
they lead you to maybe practices that are not the best practices.
I heard other people this week talk about equipment and equipment config.
We really need those. I think we need experiments in addition to surveys
as a subclass.
Genomes, how do they fit? And we're going to need more strongly typed
agents. And I'll just zoom ahead to my conclusion here.
It was a wonderful exercise to compare against that DP package, and I think it's
becoming much easier to align broader conceptual frameworks.
So that's great. One of the things that's coming out, to the chagrin of my
German colleague's conversations, is that there are certain patterns that are
coming out. Partial alignment is the norm.
Lossy exchange. If I go from TaxonWorks to DP, I'm always going to be
lossy. And
for argument's sake, I call this a law because it happens everywhere.
It's not a law, right? But how does that help us think about,
and is it a barrier to describing life at scale if we always have
to go lossy to lossy? Will SSM be adequate for
schema exchange? I hope so. It should be cool.
We see schema convergence. It's very clear to me that we have schema convergence
here. DP and TaxonWorks. If it continues, what does that tell us about the
reality of the models? And finally, when and how will AI make meaningful
contributions to the concepts in these models? So thank you.
Thanks very much, Matt.
All right, moving right along. We will have Jonas Grieb, and
he will talk about material samples and occurrences in Darwin Core data packages,
practical experiences from Dino.
Yes. Test. Can you hear me? Hello. Okay.
Hi, good afternoon. Thanks for the introduction, James.
And yeah, of course,
on behalf of all of the co-authors here,
I will share these practical experiences from Dino with you.
So,
what's the problem statement? If we look at
all of GBIF's records as of today, you see that a considerable
amount of these records in there have a record basis that
is somehow the material entity concept.
So maybe material samples, preserved specimens, or fossil specimens.
And yeah, until now, with the old Darwin Core archives,
the way this data was
mobilized often,
material data had to become occurrences in order
to
share the data and finally load it into GBIF.
And as John also explained nicely in the first presentation,
really before the introduction of the Darwin Core conceptual model,
it is difficult to disambiguate between the occurrence in
such a dataset and the material which in theory
serves as the evidence for the occurrence.
And yeah, this is problematic for datasets which
originally is really only focused on the data.
Often it is originally curated in collection management systems
and, well, many of these collection management systems don't have a concept
of occurrences. There it's just material and collecting event data.
Okay, we just saw an example of TaxonWorks.
I saw they have occurrence concept, so it's not all, but I know many.
And yeah, when we just have originally material data that
needs to be mobilized as occurrences, this creates issues with the
generation of, in theory, stable occurrence identifiers,
and often in the material data, we have incomplete or
missing event data, but the event in theory is missing to
establish an occurrence. So it is clear material entities are
not occurrences. This has also been widely discussed in
this community before,
for example, at the TWIC 2024. And the question I'm
asking today is whether these conceptual issues have now been solved
by the Darwin Core conceptual model and the data package format
from a practical perspective.
Specifically, we want to look at this set of classes or
tables in Darwin Core data packages, very similar to the graphic you've
also seen before.
The great news is really for data publishers with
material data that we now have a specific point where we can
put the data in the material. But also you can see that
there's quite a set of complex relationships and we want to
explore the practicability of sharing data in this
format from the point of view of,
for example, Natural History Museum, which has material data
in a collection management system.
The use case collection management system in this presentation is Dino.
That's
a CMS that is being developed by the Dino Consortium since
2014.
Just some institutions who decided to join forces to create a modern and
open and collaborative collection management framework for both
specimen and sample-based research.
The Dino's governance is also defined in an MOU to ensure
that the software has sustainability also beyond the
involvement of individual persons.
In Dino, what is special about it is
we call it the simplistic data model.
So Dino tries to represent material object histories as
sequences of material object states and
sequences from one state to another.
Sorry, and processes from one state to another.
These processes can be collecting or subsampling, extracting, and so on.
What does this mean in practice? You see on the right side a highly simplified
extraction of Dino's database schema.
The core entity really is the material sample, which just
like the material entity, serves as a umbrella term for both
specimens and any other kind of samples.
Material samples in Dino can be linked to collecting events.
They can be linked also to other material samples to represent such
subsampling processes. A material sample in Dino may
include one or several organisms, and determinations
are applied on these organisms in the material sample.
Now I want to show you two very practical
examples of data. How is it in Dino, and how can it be
transformed into something in the
Darwin Core data package format? This first example that you see
here
is a material sample, which represent actually a molecular sample
that was extracted from something.
So it has a parent material sample, a tissue sample
preserved in alcohol, which in turn also has a parent material sample,
which is a cataloged specimen of a fruit bat in a
mammalogy collection.
Now,
what you see on this slide is really the same information as on the
previous slide, but according to DINA's
internal database schema, that's the upper and the left part of
the slide.
You will see again three blue boxes.
They represent three material samples.
They have a relationship between them via the parent material
sample field,
and we also have an organism with a determination in the scientific name.
On the right lower part, you see how this data would be
transformed in Darwin Core data package.
And it works very well. Material samples just become material
entities.
We can model the relationships between them via the
derived from material entity field.
And that works very well. It just imposed
some minor questions. For example, is it sufficient,
like I did here, to link only the parent material
sample of such a chain to the event where it was collected?
Or would we need to repeat this information in every row,
where it can also
simply be deducted that any child material sample
originates from the same event?
It's a small detail, but maybe it requires for additional
usage conventions for Darwin Core data packages in such cases.
The second example is a little bit more complex, what we can handle in DINA.
In this case, it's a material sample which represents a specimen in a
Crustacea collection.
There's some collecting event information, and there are two organisms
in this
material sample.
This is a mud shrimp, and also it often
occurs together with a certain type of clam.
And in this material sample, these two organisms have been
collected together and also preserved together.
But we have, in the end, still two individual entities,
each with their own determination and determination histories.
Go over this one. How does it look like in Darwin Core data
packages?
Well, again, on the left upper side, you see a material sample.
In DINA, we call these the two organisms contained
in the material sample. If we transform this to Darwin Core
data packages,
well, at the moment, we need to map our organism concept also to
material entities. When we do this, you see here again, we
have three rows in the material table.
Then we can
make use of the part of material entity
relationship in Darwin Core and express in this way
something quite similar to what we express in DINA.
So apart from maybe some
semantic blurriness, this mapping also works quite well,
in this regard. However, there was one issue, and that is that in
DINA, we not only store that it's a mud shrimp organism with its
scientific name, we also store that it's an adult male mud shrimp.
If we want to
include this information here,
there is no room in the material concept in
Darwin Core. At the moment, this would require us to
add an additional table, like a table for occurrences,
only to
include also the information about life stage and sex
in there. However, I mentioned at the beginning,
certain concerns about really generating
occurrences when in our source data format, we don't
have occurrences. That's the case for DINA.
DINA does not have the occurrence concept,
and it creates downstream issues now to generate
occurrences just for the sake of exporting the data.
So this is actually an option we are not in favor of.
I don't know what could be for this very specific, detailed case, I'm
sorry. Other options, maybe just put sex and life stage
information also on the material, but that's not according to the
Darwin Core schema, at least as of now.
I don't know if this might change in the future.
Or a third option would be to use material assertions.
It looks quite elegant to put the information there, but it imposes
also the question whether then
later downstream data consumers of this, like GBIF or
finally the end users also find the data which they are looking
for if they are specifically interested in these attributes, which in other
places in the schema have a dedicated attribute.
So this again, also, I think a solution that is possible,
but it would also require, let's say
further
agreements between data publishers of this type of material
data without occurrences, and also agreement with
downstream data processes.
With this, I already come to the conclusions.
DINA's data model is already widely aligned with the new Darwin
Core conceptual model, specifically material entity
lineage and also material entities with complex
mixed organism material
can be represented. And coming back to this
pentagon of different Darwin Core
concepts and their relationships, what is here on the right side in the
green box, this is what really works well and what is aligned
with DINA's
collection management system internal data model.
What is outside of it, the occurrences, well, it's not aligned.
And this simply would mean for us as a data publisher that in the
future we aim to mobilize our data as Darwin
Core data packages, but without occurrences.
Really focus only on the classes that are represented in our
internal data model.
And then if downstream data consumers, it could be
GBIF, if they really require occurrences,
they could use still our data, and they can generate then the
occurrences based on the data according to their
internal requirements. But for this, we need, as I
mentioned, additional conventions between the
data publishers and data consumers for
sharing this type of material data.
Thank you.
Sorry. Acknowledgments.
Thanks very much, Jonas.
Our next talk is a virtual one, so it will be
a movie.
And that comes from Katie Pearson.
It's entitled "Sharing Extended Specimen Data from Symbiota Portals
Using Registered Extensions."
Hi, my name is Katie Pearson, and I'm here to talk about extended
specimen data in Symbiota Portals and how we're sharing them by following
standards.
Symbiota is an open-source biodiversity data management software.
It's kind of a mini aggregator as well as a collection management system.
It's open source, so it's freely available on GitHub.
And it underlies about 60 or more
biodiversity portals. About 52 of them are hosted
at the University of Kansas, at the Symbiota Support Hub, and
they are used widely by over 2,000 collections to
share data with the wide world.
This is just an example of the Mid-Atlantic Herbaria Consortium, a project of
herbaria across the Mid-Atlantic region of the United States, who all share their
data via this portal.
Symbiota Portals are places where communities of practice can work together.
Many collections are sharing data alongside one another, and they are
publicly searchable, and there are many tools for creating checklists, viewing
images, mapping, et cetera.
Here's an example of a map. These are interactive, and then there are
georeferencing tools for the collection managers as well.
As I mentioned, Symbiota Portals are also collection management systems, so they
can be used as web interfaces for a database.
So they can be your primary database where you do all your data entry, your
editing, and your management. This is an example of the data entry
page, and there are many tools for georeferencing, for
connecting to the taxonomic thesaurus, et cetera.
The key design of Symbiota is that it's low barrier to entry
mobilization of data. So we're trying to make things as easy to get into
as possible because we know that collections folks' time are
limited, and their ability to
learn new systems is limited by that lack of time.
So
while we try to keep everything aligned with Darwin Core data standards, we also
want to make sure that the data's really easy to import and export.
Sometimes aligning the standards makes that even easier.
And then there are built-in publishing tools so that the data can go directly to
GBIF instead of through an integrated publishing toolkit.
So we're really trying to make things as easy as possible, low barrier to entry for
the users.
So today, I'm going to be talking about how Symbiota stores and shares
data that's kind of considered extended data.
So not the primary who, what, where of the specimens, but the
data on top of that, such as annotations, such as media, material
sample, traits, things like that.
And this is, again, a picture of the data entry page, and
you can see these tabs along the top, and that is how we visualize the
extended data for the collection managers.
So they will be seeing these different tabs, and that's where they can manage the
extended data.
Some of the data extensions are included on the main entry page.
For example, additional identifiers can be seen in this kind of table
within the table here, but most of the extensions are viewable on these
tabs.
So this is the primary
data package or data view. Most of it is
occurrence-based. It's occurrence-based rather than event-based because
occurrences kind of have traditionally been along with the
idea of the specimen.
And we have occurrences as kind of the main core, and then all of the extensions
that I'm going to talk about today include kind of the old-fashioned multimedia and
identifications. But some of the newer implementations are
using extended measurement or fact, material sample, resource relationship, and the
alternative identifiers extension.
So we now support data from all of these extensions in Symbiota Portals.
So first I'll talk about the two general ones, are multimedia and
identifications. These are pretty self-explanatory. I go back to this page.
There is a tab for media. There's a tab for the determination history,
and this is the identification history of those specimens.
So these are pretty easy for folks to wrap their minds
around. They've been around for a very long time, and they will keep
track of
how many times that specimen has been identified and any of the multimedia
associated with those records.
Since those ones are somewhat easy to think about, I'm going to talk a little bit
longer about the other newer ones.
So after the multimedia and identifications, those have been around for a long
time. We implemented the extended measurement or fact extension,
and the reason for this is that we had a project
that was trying to capture phenological data from herbarium
specimens. And so we were trying to wrap our heads around how we might be able to
capture that data in a useful way. And really it came down to
the extended measurement or fact extension really
incorporated everything that we needed to.
We, in fact, looked into developing a new standard for phenology, and just
everything seemed to be
packageable according to the extended measurement or fact just fine.
So,
all of these extensions that I'm talking about, they are registered extensions.
GBIF has a nice page with all these registered extensions on it.
And we found that the extended measurement or fact, it
incorporated or was able to incorporate phenological data just fine because we
could link it to measurement types and measurement values and
who did it How they did it, and whether there were any notes.
And then these ID values, which are found in the extended measurement or
fact extension, could be linked to ontologies.
And so we found that the phenological data could be really well captured by the
extended measurement or fact, as long as we had some great
ontologies and controlled vocabularies that we could store in these ID fields.
Well, they're going in the type and the value, but they are linked to the
ontologies through the ID fields.
And some implementation of this is that project was able to capture lots of
phenological data for the herbarium specimens in that portal using
some new tools that were developed, some trait scoring tools in the portal.
And then now that data is available for public reuse for research.
We were able to do some analyses of phenological trends
using all that data in that extension.
So it was pretty easy to use and incorporate and analyze from there.
Okay. Symbiota also has the material sample extension, and this has
largely been used by the NEON, the National Ecological Observatory Network in the
United States, and they needed to track the DNA extractions
largely and the sample extractions from their specimens.
And so this has been enabled in the NEON portal.
But there's also many other portals that it's available in too.
And so that's like an up-and-coming extension that folks are using
to track the genetic subsamples and sometimes just tissue
subsamples of
the specimens. And so this one actually, I think it has a lot of potential to
continue to be used for subsampling of specimens.
Here is just a screenshot of what the material sample module looks like, and
most of them are elements of the GGBN material sample extension.
We also have the support for the alternative identifiers extension.
And the need for this came about because we found that folks were using the other
catalog numbers field, which previously was just a field,
to store a lot of different identifiers.
For example, national forest numbers or national parks numbers they
were capturing in there. But they were really difficult to search because if you're
just searching a text field
that has a lot of concatenated values in it, it's very hard to find.
So we ended up
turning this into an identifier value somewhat table.
So it's a different table in the structure now.
And it's actually really well-aligned with an existing
Darwin Core extension, the alternative identifiers extension, which is
super easy. It's basically just three or four fields saying,
"Here is the
core ID, and then the additional identifier and the additional identifier name."
So while this is ballooning up the number of extensions, it makes it way
easier to find those values when you're searching for them.
Okay. Lastly, I'm going to talk about the resource relationship extension that
we've been able to use in Symbiota portals, and this has been really key for
capturing extended specimen data, and so we're really excited to see where this one
goes. So we are using the Darwin Core resource relationship extension,
which is very confusing to look at because all of the names sound similar,
in English at least. And so, it does take quite a bit
of time to wrap your mind around it.
But the idea is, is that you're providing an identifier to a thing,
a thing it's related to, and the relationship of that thing to the thing that it's
related to. And then, of course, there's IDs for all those things.
So we've seen some really cool implementation for this, is
you are able to make relationships from a specimen record to
something else. And that can be either another specimen record or completely
external,
or a
specimen record some other place, or a completely different thing,
so a different site or a different reference or something like that.
So one implementation of this has been the Carlquist project,
where
a library and an herbarium, actually two herbaria, are coming together and
trying to link all this field data, these slides data, this research and field
notebook data to the specimen records that were already in Symbiota portals.
So this is a close-up photo that was taken from the same event
as this specimen record. So you can see there's a linkage
between the
specimen record and this photo. So we're able to have these
cross-linkages, and all of those cross-linkages can be
managed or can be
discovered in this extension.
We've developed some new tools. As you can imagine, having all of these different
data types
means that you have to develop ways of ingesting that data.
So we have a new importer. And then the export tools too.
For every table you create, you have to be able to share that too.
But because these are in Darwin Core extensions, those extensions are immediately
visible on GBIF, which has been really cool to see.
The main challenge with all this is that no longer can all extended data be
included in a single CSV upload. So we had to discontinue some old
options in favor of new options. And the biggest issue with this is that there's a
balance between robustness and aligning with standards and
user-friendliness.
But I would say one of the wins is that most of these needs came
up independently, and we were able to find a Darwin Core extension that actually
perfectly fit those needs with a little bit of thought.
So definitely encourage looking up existing standards before developing
your own.
Thanks very much, Katie, virtually.
Okay, so the next three talks are related.
And because of that, there's three of them that are spreading the topic.
And they'll be a little shorter, but
I'm sure we will learn a lot. And the first
is coming from Birgit.
Yeah, you changed your order, right? Okay. Please go ahead.
Yeah. Thanks. My name is Birgit Rach, and I'm
the digital collection manager of the LIB in Bonn.
So I give the first talk of three about the Diversity
Workbench, and so I give more an overview on how we use
Diversity Workbench.
So, but what is we?
We are a Leibniz Institute for Analysis of Biodiversity Change.
We are a research museum in the Leibniz Association in Germany,
and we are located at two sites, one in Bonn and Hamburg.
We consist of several sections. We
have really different zoological collections, but also a
botanical, geological, mineralogical, and paleontological
collection.
And we have a biobank. This is storing tissue and DNA,
but also living cells and all of
this in cryopreservation.
Additional to that, we have environmental sample bank,
where the malaise traps
samples are stored
and in Biohistoricum, so a lot of
old books.
Together to that, we have several current scientific
projects, and we are one of the 10
GFBioData centers. So we have additional external
data. So to sum up, we have a lot of
heterogeneous data.
To store them, we use the Diversity Workbench for now for
more than 10 years.
The key features
are that it's in the relational database system.
It's developed in Munich,
Germany, also. It is open source, so you all can use it.
It has the capability to use multiple tenants,
and you have a really granular right management system
inside.
One of the key features is also the import wizard,
so that we have customizable imports.
And we can link to really a diverse
amount of different repositories.
And in addition to that, we also developed an
API which
my colleague, Björn Quast, is
providing in the next talk.
In this talk, I will focus on the module diversity
collection.
So, but this is not the only component of our
collection infrastructure. We have also several other
databases in our house.
For the media and PDFs, we use
the digital asset management system Filer
and Geneious for the
sequence data and, as I said, the ASV registry for the
ASV tables.
For the publication, we use the Biocase Provider software and
also the GBIF IPT tool.
And of course, we have our own collection catalog online.
Here you can see
a view of the import visit in DC. This is one of
the ways to get the data into DC.
We have aligned workflows between our different
collections, and of course, you can also
enter the data manually and as a new
way about the API.
A short view how the data looks like in
DC. You can see the collection data, the analysis data,
and the geographic reference
instant on an integrated map.
And you can also link to different taxonomic
references or the media asset management system
and diverse other sources.
We have different collections, so we have to connect
between these collections. For this purpose, we developed
by our own script
also to reference the data
between the data management system and
the Geneious or the sequence data system for the
laboratory data.
And of course, to synchronize the data between
Diversity Workbench and Filer
for the image data.
Connection to other public repositories can also be done
and are shown here.
To publish them, we have,
of course, a human-readable version, but also the setup
stable identifier is integrated.
We provide them as RBF and JSON files.
The Disco DOI is planned but not established at the
moment.
So with that, we developed a workflow together with all the
other GFBioData centers.
This workflow integrated the Biocase Provider software to map to
ABCD,
and also we are using the GBIF IPT to map
to Darwin Core.
And of course, we have a DOI assignment to all our datasets.
And with that, we can publish to several
portal the same data at one time.
But of course,
this is not all
doing easy peasy. We have also challenges.
One of that, that not all data types are covered in
Diversity Workbench, so we developed our own database.
And a complex database often lead to a
complex interface, too complex for a lot of our
user.
And there is another problem, there is no client
available for macOS and Linux. So we are at the
moment at the development of a browser-based interface to solve
this.
As I said, we have developed own scripts for some specific
software and to do the data exchange between
several DC instances.
And we have to
focus on some
specific requirements of
several collectors, several custodians, and
we provide for them
customized import schemas and the possibility,
but not the must, to link to taxonomic
references.
Of course, we have some
methods to ensure the data quality.
So for example, we provide templates for controlled
vocabularies. We check before we import the data
several times. We connect to several
references to ensure the consistency, and
there is also checks by the publishing portals, for
example, the GFBio portal and the GFBio
validator.
But last is
there can also be changing APIs from other sides
or links, and there you only have to be keep up to date.
There's no other possibility.
That's all from my side.
So I'm just in time. Thank you for listening, and I
handle over to my colleague, Björn Quast.
Yes, thank you. My talk
is
about work in progress on something that tries
to connect
our collection management system a little bit more with
the users on the other side.
And,
okay. As Birgit told a moment before,
the Diversity Workbench tries to
provide a collection management system for
all data
associated, or all information associated with
collection specimens. So there
is information about loans, about the
storage location, about identifications and taxonomy,
and so on.
Sorry.
Yes, and as you can see, the interface to
that in the moment is restricted to a client
software on Windows. And on the other hand,
it's structured
according to the different concepts of
information. So you have
areas for the specimen tree or areas for
where the things are stored or for images, for
media, and so on, and it looks a little
bit complex for the user. It
changes when users go into other
concepts too.
And
we also, as Birgit shows, have different
pipelines to publish the data. Here, the
way is always over multiple format
transformations.
Pipelines are used to filter by
access rights, by projects, by
the different collections that we have, and to
connect them in the end, media and external
resources.
A problem is that there's no way back
with these pipelines in the end. We
developed an online catalog that
is based on our Diversity Workbench
installation
and tries to make
the data accessible for our users
in the museum and for the public.
We implemented something for
adjustable filters where you can choose what
filters you want to see. We have
suggestions in the filter, so you can--
oh, yeah, a pointer. Where you can
type in something and then it
suggests you where it can be found.
And we have more complex queries, Boolean
queries with sub-queries too.
You will get these tables
about the results, and you can adjust what you can see in
the tables, and you can download
everything you have in your results, all the complete data
in a
CSV file. Oh.
For each
specimen, we have a page then that shows
detailed information like barcode analyses
or images, and it's connected via a
CITA stable identifier.
So one challenge at the moment for us is to do a
redesign. As you have seen before, it's a little bit
ugly, and the challenge here is to put
scientific data into a
format that can be easily viewed by mobile
devices.
So one idea is to have something like this
visual data exploration, where you use charts to
filter out information. So we
use an Elasticsearch index to
fill this portal. That is
another transformation, but as you will see in a moment,
it's much easier to update, and it makes
ingest possible for us. We have to
implement the complex structure of
access rights within this, because Diversity
Workbench has several levels of
access rights on different concepts, on different
tables, and so on.
And
then we decided to also put a
REST API on this database. That
is
mainly because we want to have variable user
interfaces on a fixed data
interface, and we figured out that we can use a
similar JSON structure for the Elasticsearch and the
API.
We
decide to work on concepts with the
endpoints of the API rather than on single
tables. So, for example, we have here
four tables for the collection event here,
and these are structured into a schema
and
filled together as a single endpoint.
So data ingest in Diversity
Workbench is a process that can
be really sophisticated because you can
decide on single tables or
concepts what you want to do with it, insert
always new data, update existing data,
update, or if exist or
insert or attach data. And
to do that a little bit easier, we try to
implement a schema, how to
decide when to update and when to
insert. And that's mainly based on
constraints like in
relational databases.
So
we have
used that API for our SV
registry, where data on OTU
tables connected to
occurrences and connected to
identifications are collected
and published, and we use the
API to ingest
this data into the Diversity
Workbench.
And
this ends up then in the data
in the Diversity Workbench with a basic
set at the moment, so basic occurrence data,
analysis methods, identifications, images,
and collections. And with that, I thank you for
your
attention. Thank you very much.
Okay. So now I start our third talk about
Diversity Workbench. And
so
as we've already seen,
the Diversity Workbench, it's a data management system that
consists of various modules,
and each is
designed for a different data type.
So, for example, you have a module for occurrence data, one for taxonomic and
checklist data, one for trade data, and so on.
But I would like to draw attention now to the fact that this is a
very complex relational database or
database system. And as you can see here
on this slide,
there's only a very small selection of the entity relation
diagrams that are underlying the Diversity Workbench.
And so when it is coming time to publish the data from the
Diversity Workbench,
we were thinking about what would be the best way, and Darwin Core was
always too slow. So we decided many years ago
to just choose the ABCD standard. ABCD stands
for Access to Biological
Collection Data. So we were creating this
publishing pipeline.
So we have up here the modules of the Diversity
Workbench linked to each other, where we exported the data,
filtered it during this. So filtering means that
there was the possibility to withhold data, withhold restricted
data, to anonymize any personal data,
to round any coordinates, something like this.
And then the data were stored in a PostgreSQL database,
one database for each data package.
And afterwards, we are using, or we are still using, the Biocase
provider software and mapping there the data to the
ABCD standard. So we get an ABCD XML file
that's harvested by GBIF and also by
NFDI4Biodiversity, so the National Research Data Infrastructure in
Germany.
So we were using this pipeline for many years,
but this pipeline also has some limitations,
as you can see here.
So we have
some very important data set metadata were not,
or not fully, represented or displayed in the GBIF portal.
So for example, some multiple global identifiers were not shown,
and also the associated persons at institutions, including the roles.
We had to enter them manually in the GBIF portal.
They were not just harvested together with all the other
metadata. Then also, relations between different
data were not displayed. They have been in the ABCD XML file, but they
were not displayed in GBIF. And also, the publication
of a data paper is not very easy. I did it with a few researchers, and you
have to type in many data manually.
They cannot just get from the GBIF
website.
So now we were quite happy because Darwin Core Data Package aims to
combine the strengths of both approaches, and
it introduces a more flexible and semantically
explicit framework for biodiversity data
publishing. So we were thinking about why we should not try it.
So this is the data flow we're using, and we are staying
with these parts of the data flow and just trying to
use here, instead of the Biocase provider software, the IPT
tool and the Darwin Core Data Package instead of ABCD.
So we get a Darwin Core Data Package.
So we tried it. We installed an IPT, not the official
one, but a test version, because only the test version includes, at the
moment, the Darwin Core Data Package.
So we were installing the test version of the IPT,
and
that's what was our first step. So that's a screenshot of the IPT
installation. So first, we added our
source data.
What you can see here are all the tables from the Diversity Workbench, from the
PostgreSQL data.
So we accessed it directly via SQL.
And second,
we had to do the mapping of all this data.
So the first one is always the Diversity Workbench
table, and the second one is the Darwin Core Data Package
table. And as you can see, it's often quite similar, but not all the time.
So for example, we need to separate our
observation data and the physical specimen data.
That's separated here in the Darwin Core Data Package.
It was together in the original one,
and it leaded to occurrence data and material
data down here. Then some things have been together.
They share, for example, the event up here, the identification, and
also the agents. And then we had to
unite some
informations like, for example-- Oops, sorry.
This was not
what was I want to be.
So we have here our analysis and up here
our processing, and we had to combine these things in this
material assertion. So we did this mapping
to this Darwin Core Data Package, and what we got is this
entity relation diagram you can see here,
and also the first
data, or prototype.
These are the data of a data package we already published in the past using
this
ABCD Biocase provider software data pipeline,
and now we tried it with this way. And our next
steps now will be
to
get in contact with GBIF, because we would like to compare.
We have this data published at the moment as
an ABCD data file, and now we would like to publish
them in a sandbox
using this
Darwin Core Data Package pipeline and then compare the result.
What is shown in GBIF, what is shown differently?
Yeah, what's better, what's perhaps not so good.
Then perhaps we will also have to adjust our mapping as we are doing at the moment.
Yeah, it's just a prototype, a first try.
And, yeah, what we would also like to discuss at the metadata of
the data package,
you have to enter them manually in the
IPT tool. So it's not possible to map them from our
Diversity Workbench database, so that's also something we would like to discuss
with GBIF. And if this
workflow will be working well, then the next step would be
that the data are also published to different other portals, like the
NFDI4Biodiversity GFBio Data Portal, and then we will have
to adjust this data flow as well.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks. Thanks very much to Birgit and Björn and
Tanja for that
suite of talks. This is the last talk before the break.
We are ridiculously on time. Thanks to everybody for
that. And this is a recorded talk that's coming next.
I don't know if it's pronounced Ye or exactly, but Ye Li.
Good morning, everyone. My name is Ye Li.
From the Korea National University of Heritage.
Today, I will present our study about semantic
integration of natural heritage with 3D data of
Bio-City collections.
It aims to transport the 3D specimens from isolated
visual resource into connected knowledge assets like
the biological information, heritage context, and digital
production process.
To establish the scope of this study, UNESCO
defined the World Natural Heritage through outstanding
natural beauty, distinctive ecosystem, biological
diversity, and geological value.
Its significance extends to habit
conservation, climatic research, international
population, and sustainability to our region.
While criteria assess the beauty,
arts, history, ecological process,
and diversity.
And also, this criteria explain why scientific
records of nature can also carry heritage
value.
This distinctive becomes clear
when the natural history is compared with heritage,
like the former explains
how arts and living organizations change,
whereas the latter concerns values formed through
human interaction, preservation, and interpretations.
The
specimen bridge the two because
it records biological evidence while retaining the
history of the collection, curation, research, and
exhibitions.
Once understood in this way, the next question is
how such evidence should be digitized and managed.
Existing services address different parts of the
task.
The first, GBIF, provide
accuracy records.
BHL, offer historical literature.
The
Smithsonian offers the interactive 3D model, and
finally, Disco connects European collections as
fair digital specimens.
Together, they show a progression
from real-time observation and documentary context
to three-dimensional semantic resource, but they
still operated across separated systems.
So we defined these
problems like the natural heritage information
is currently distributed across different institutions and
projects, and also differences in the data quality and
management structure, and combined with continued use of
low-quality 3D data limiting
interoperation.
These separation levels of low-quality
2D/3D records inconveniently
classification practice
from one each other.
In response, our framework combines AI-assisted
3D capture with an archive-based museum platform to
support endangered and rare specimens.
Its implementation depends on the common classification schema,
an integration database, an application layer,
quality control, sharing, and reuse, and the metadata
describing the production process.
For the 3D capture, we assembled about
800 physical specimens representing, and about
40 specimens from seven institutions, and selected the
target through expert consultations.
Because their size ranging from small insects
to large mammals and birds,
we adapted the acquisition setup to each size group.
Now, we present a photometric-based 3D data production
process.
This consists of four layers from the raw data
capturing, and then camera capturing with multiple
points, and then we do this
registration for making the mesh
type of the 3D, and finally, we generated
the mesh type of the
correctly
3D data.
This slide about the example of the 3D data
according to the size,
and the bottom shows that
some of the 3D data attributes
like metadata and the final data table.
This processed
semantic model organizes information into three
layers: data, metadata, and paradata.
The data class includes nature, specimen, and
accuracy, representing natural objects, the physical
specimen, and the collection observation events.
The metadata class includes heritage and resource, which
connects the specimen to its heritage value and
related documents and digital resource.
Finally, the paradata class includes the project
institution and item representing the
digitization project and the process.
This structure transforms isolated 3D files
into a contextual knowledge graph connecting natural objects,
physical specimens, and digital production processes.
This model aligns the six complementary standards and
platforms like Dublin Core, OpenDS,
Morphosys, but we also connected and
mixed it with
the cultural heritage standards like Europeana Pro, the Dublin
Core, the CIDOC CRM. That's why we
show these collaborations between these
different fields of the global standards.
This page shows
how the global standards adjust into our
extended distributed natural
resource. We performed a one-to-one mapping
between the reference standards and our model.
We then also visualized our database with
Neo4j.
This amount of the knowledge graph, about
2,400
nodes and about
3,600
relations.
And then we also made three
examples of applications like
CMS integration, the specimen information,
and the 3D asset and digitization histories.
A user-adapted system recommending related
information, and finally, map-based
visualizing location-based variations.
So we just wanted the user to begin with the 3D
specimen and extend it to its
morphological, ecological, and
institutional context, making the asset the entry
point for explanations.
Finally, we are thinking about our study, the connected
3D assets, about the specimen with the
specimen occupancy environments
and the heritage information, heritage context,
and also the production process, while
improving interoperability
across from the biodiversity,
heritage, and the digital
environments.
We demonstrate this approach using about
800 of 1,640 specimens from
the 300 of
840 specimens across seven
institutions.
So we have planned future work like
validating the model,
applying AI-based metadata enrichment and
quality assessments, and evaluating it through
the PROS institutional pilot
programs. It's not only for the Korean government,
we also want to extend our project
into the global markets.
Thank you for listening to my presentation.
If you have any questions, please scan the QR code.
Thank you.
So thanks very much to the speakers for the first session.
We're a little bit ahead of time, but because of miking, et cetera, I think we'll
just leave it there. Like I said, after the next session, there's several more good
presentations coming.
We'll have time for discussion, time for some thinking about...
We've been focusing on the data package and seen several
different ways of dealing with that. That diversity is great.
It's a chance for all of us to see this, think deeply about this, ask
questions, and know who to bug once you get out of here.
So let's just take a break. Please come back
promptly after, and we'll keep going.
All right. It
is
actually time for us to start, but you see what coffee breaks do.
So we'll let people slowly come in.
We do have some extra time, of course, for discussion.
We have one live talk and then two
recorded talks,
and
then lively discussion.
Stine, I think we can wait a minute or two, just let a few more people
walk up the stairs.
All right. Well, let's not push it too much.
I'll welcome Stine Dupont to the stage,
and he's going to talk about old habits and new visions, exploring the
Recode data model, future integration, and data enhancement.
Thank you very much.
This is all going to go wrong. We'll see how it works.
Thank you for joining.
Those who don't know Recode, Recode is a program at the museum that is aiming to
build a new collections management system.
I am the program manager of that.
It's been quite a journey. I was here two years ago talking about it, and I thought
I'd come back and show a bit about where we were.
I realize there's less data model in this one than the previous talks,
but there are a bit of visualizations of what the system looks like.
So we started back in 2019. We are currently here now,
and hopefully going live at the beginning of next year. So very exciting.
Going to start building the production. So what you'll see is the UAT environment.
I do want to talk a bit about the supplier.
Cute
little slime mold. I'm not going to delve too long in that.
We do have them in the system. I realized we didn't actually have slime molds in
our system, so I had to build a separate
phylogeny for it, or a taxonomy for it.
This is from the supplier side.
This is giant, isn't it? I do apologize.
What you see is what we're actually really building is that common
fabric at the bottom. That's really what we're building.
And hopefully what we're getting to is we're going to start unlocking those
things that we've all
been talking about. That would be really, really exciting, including
integrating with models, integrating with AI, building our orchestration,
and simply building stuff in the system that sits on top
of what it is we're building.
Before I show you some of the systems, some of the things we've been doing,
it really did become a museum-wide changing program, not only because we
decided to completely revamp the data structure that we had underneath
after 20 years
of using our current system,
which is fundamentally different.
We decided to do a huge data
model normalization. We optimized our procedures.
We are dealing with the data debt, knowledge debt, technology debt that
we had, but also entirely infrastructure at the back end.
Happy to talk more about that in a minute.
What I thought would be fun is just talking a bit about the normalization.
So
these numbers are real. I've seen the spreadsheets.
Our current system has something like 70 record types just for objects,
with something like 54,000 fields, and that's because they're
replicated across those 70
different record types. When we start digging into that and removing those fields
that aren't used, we end up with something like 6,500.
We've been through those line by line.
We end up with something like
600 fields or 700 fields. And what we end up
with is
four target collection object entities, so biological,
geological, extraterrestrial, human-made, with a subset of field sections
underneath that. So huge condensing of that.
But the truth is we've done that across the whole system.
These are taken from the master data dictionary that we have that our data
architect produces.
If you just look at our previous system modules, about 55
modules or entities there
Most of our fields map one-to-one.
You can see some of them actually start condensing our current system
fields into one field in our new system.
We then end up with
a lot more fragmented entities that are unique in themselves
and that we can start building with.
So that's for us at least what it looks like when we take a big flat structure and
we sort of bring it in. If I were to draw the connections and relationships between
that, it all just collapses into one. Everything's linked. We all know that.
That's what builds the complexity in our system, is that every single entity is
linked to multiple others.
So some of the things that we've done, I'll jump into the system, just show you a
bit of the system, which some of the things that I think are cool, is
we've transitioned to using true relationships, instead of just having fields with
a valid-- sorry,
a value that defines where it's linked to.
We've decoupled the object from the processes.
We're enforcing stricter hierarchies,
both on taxonomy and locations model.
We're establishing some controlled movement controls.
This is very important to us as a museum, of course, as we move things around.
But also really redeveloping the procedures at the back end, which is quite
important to us,
because that's part of managing our museum.
What I wanted to show you is, I'll just show you a couple of videos, one about the
data model viewer, which is something that we've built into the system.
I'll show you a bit about people, show you a bit about the processes, and then show
you a bit about our bulk integration
template builder, which I think is rather cool.
There's a little bit of preamble there.
Essentially, we're going to go up into the corner.
We're going to go to the data model.
You'll see
what I hope becomes a tool for our users to understand how the
system actually fits together. It's going to be a fundamentally different system.
That's too complex, but if we sort of just pare that down, we select myself as
a user, we select agent, which is people, organization, software agents.
We remove the depth of our relationships.
And to start with, we can just remove relationships altogether so that we can just
see the different entities that are relevant to agents. So there we are.
That's what we have in agents. We have people, organizations, software agents, got
the field values there. If I then put back the relationships, we should then be
able to see how that's interlinked.
This is a bit too granular for our users, but it allows us to extract that
information and use that in other visualizations around the system, because we've
had a wide use of dashboards.
We also have other kinds of entities that are massive.
This is acquisition. This is a process.
This is meant to be developing the information of a process over time through
multiple steps, so it becomes large.
But this is also why we had the problem with our collections
objects that were so flat, because we had acquisitions in there.
We had tons of fields for a process on an object that
ideally was something completely different.
I'm going to jump over to people just to show you that.
I should have chosen collection object.
The way that works is we have overview screens, of course.
We've got whitespace, lovely whitespace for all our AI-generated data and
everything else that we want to put in the future.
This is essentially designed for the computer screens that we have.
Jumping, you can see links to other people.
Here you can see me linked to Han Solo.
You can go in and look at-- this is UAT.
You can go in and look at the relationship of me and Han Solo, and what you'll see
is that he's a long-lost son of mine, which is great.
But this allows us to establish multiple relationship between the same
entities with a record, an historic record, that we can follow as to
how that has changed.
You can see here we're looking at something different, all the processes I'm
involved with. You can start looking at a number of other things.
This is--
I can't remember what that is.
So that's how most entities are structured.
Processes, however,
we have a workflow engine behind it, which was one of the things we wanted from the
start.
And we wanted this because we have a number of processes that need to operate
within the museum to make it work. Starts with a smaller module where you enter
your unique ID, et cetera, it saves that, and then you can actually step
into the workflows, and
I think I'm going to jump to the attachments, but then I'm going to jump to the
actual tasks that you can see,
where you can start seeing-- I want to show three different types.
So I'm going to show one, which is the acquisition here, which is a parallel flow.
Ideally, what we want, as you can see there, we want people to be able to fill out
all the information they have in one go and not be dependent between steps.
Okay, cool.
But we do, of course, have other processes where we want people to
follow distinct steps. So if we take something like research loan
in or research loan out, what you'll see is we no longer have those
parallel tasks that you can complete willy-nilly, but
you have to actually follow
the steps.
Should have cut these videos a little shorter.
Let's just jump into that.
Boom, boom.
Hopefully, we jump that. So again, screen, fill in data.
Those are all the tabs. Those are linked to all the tasks that you'll see,
but you cannot complete one task, there you go,
before you've actually gone through the workflow, and that's intentional because
this is compliance and regulation, right?
People need to do things in a certain order so that it can come back and bring
things back. So we've got these different types of processes.
We've also got a silent process, which is our location and movement
control. By silent, just means it happens in the background, right?
So what we're doing is we need to be able to take an object or a box of
object with multiple things in it.
We need to move it, and basically, all we need to do is we need to say,
"This thing is going from here to there," and then everything moves and that's
recorded, and we need to have a movement history. And that's what we're doing here.
So we're basically taking that object is there. We're going to start a new process.
We're going to say object move.
And then we're going to define where it moves, why it moves, and a little bit of
text if we want.
So I'm going to use a code. I know which cabinet it's going to.
And then the process essentially happens in the background.
So the user doesn't have to jump in and look at it.
It's meant to be a very quick way of managing the collection.
Let's go there. And then
I'm going to skip to the last one, which is our bulk ingest,
which is a hugely important thing to us, not only because of all the
digitization that happens, but because this is a way that we bulk
update, delete,
fix data in the system, which means we have to have a quite
versatile way of doing it. So I'm just going to jump over to that.
I'm going to show you the template, not the process itself.
You've just seen the process. We've built a template that allows us to build the
CSV and the JSON that's outputted.
It's got dynamic error handling. It's got all the different fields
in there.
So essentially, a data manager will create this for a user, and the user
can then fill in all that data, and then the system can then suck it in.
It creates all the entities with all the fields are available in there.
It's got links.
We've also got special functions in there, which we want.
This is hugely important to us, not only for the ingest of data, but also the
JSON that comes out of this can be used for other
APIs and other things that we want to use outside of the system, which is
fantastic. I think I'm slightly running out of time, so I'm going to jump to the
last two slides. Happy to talk about any of this afterwards and show.
It's not a problem. You can just come up.
My laptop is charging, so should be fine.
But essentially, yeah, so you can see the errors there.
We're creating two entities without any links. We shouldn't be doing that.
But once we create a link, that goes away.
Going to jump to the last two slides.
So essentially, this is a process, but it's a process where the user basically just
commits a document, and then the data manager goes through everything else.
What I'm really looking forward to with the fact that we are almost close to
having this system and going live is to build all those extra
things on top that already exist. What I showed you in that diagram,
including
image annotation, which already exists, the relationship validation, which
we're building. We've got the bulk operations within the system, not what I just
showed, reporting, documenting, but essentially, that
is
a screenshot of our business studio, which is the admin layer,
where you can see we've already got integrations, AI.
We've got access to our data model, the search fields.
We have access to these things so we can start rapidly building onto
the basic infrastructure that we've done, and that's one of the things that we're
really looking forward to, which is going to require quite a
bit of institutional governance as well.
Because one thing we don't want to do is come back to the siloed environment we had
before. So agreeing on fields, et cetera, needs to be done
by everybody.
And I think that's it. So, and thank you guys to you and to Doxis and
Q as well. We've been following Q for a while.
So thank you. I'll take questions if we have time.
So we'll do questions at the end.
Yes.
After the next two, yeah.
So the next two talks are recorded.
They are both by Erika Krimmel. She's filling in for a colleague,
so
she's recorded them both.
And then after that, we'll start discussing.
Hello. My name is Erika Krimmel. I'm presenting
today on behalf of myself, my colleague Teresa, about what we feel is the
unruliness of higher geography in Darwin Core.
Just a note, this talk stems from work we have both been doing with Arctos, a
collaborative collections management system, but we aren't representing any sort of
official Arctos position here.
So starting things off with a little bit of fun.
What we often think of as higher geography matters to our community,
primarily because it contextualizes a locality.
For example, in the image on this slide, the context for a locality might
be county, tribal lands, drainage, assessed water, et cetera.
Localities, often, they intermix human, governmental, and physical
geography, as well as text descriptions with more precise coordinate
systems.
Users of biodiversity really need all of this context to serve
research, to encourage ethical practices, enable legal compliance,
all of that.
And higher geography is frequently a useful first-pass filter.
Given that we're thinking about higher geography as used in the TDWG community,
looking at the existing model in Darwin Core is our focus today.
So within Darwin Core, we want to hone in on geography, which includes quite a few
terms, notably those within the location and the geological context
classes.
The terms highlighted in red are those we would loosely consider part of higher
geography, although this already is getting unruly.
There's both a term, Darwin Core higher geography, and a group of
terms that we think are typically included in the concept of higher
geography.
So looking just at the Darwin Core term, higher geography, definition
is open to a lot of interpretation.
A list of geographic names less specific than the information captured in the
Darwin Core locality term.
Users often translate this as a concatenated list of values from all
those other parsed-out fields, like Darwin Core continent, country, et cetera.
But the definition also leaves room for values that, in fact, don't have a tome in
another term,
as is shown in the example with Parque Nacional Nahuahuapi.
And
what terms to include in a concatenated list for higher geography is a
decision that every user makes independently.
It's intentionally flexible,
but that flexibility leads to inconsistency and the Darwin Core term itself
being somewhat of a trash basket or a treasure trove, depending
on what kind of geography you're dealing with.
Okay, so perhaps it's easier to think about what does not belong in higher
geography.
An inverse of the term definition might suggest anything as
specific or more specific than the information captured in Darwin Core
locality shouldn't go here.
So we could safely exclude terms that describe a Darwin Core locality in detail.
For example,
maximum elevation in meters or verbatim locality, as well as
probably the whole geological context class.
We can also probably exclude terms related to geospatial data, although there are
scenarios where that data might be less granular than the locality,
like if the specimen was geo-referenced to a county centroid.
And we can exclude terms that capture identifiers, since they typically exist in
parallel to other terms.
Okay.
Circling back to what maybe belongs.
The current definition and usage notes imply that the terms shown on
this slide do belong in Darwin Core higher geography.
We could loosely group these into terms related to human geography,
so how people use, organize, give meaning to space, and those related to
physical geography, which refers to the natural systems of Earth's surface,
landforms, climate, water, soils, et cetera.
But are these terms really the scope of Darwin Core higher geography?
Human and physical geography often, but don't always, have natural
hierarchies. So,
jamming everything into a single term, it's a bit odd.
And if we already have explicit terms for these kinds of information,
why are we putting it in two places?
Add in the factor that we frequently have more information about human and
physical geography than fits neatly into existing Darwin Core terms.
For example, on the human side, we have administrative areas, parks,
government lands, exclusive economic zones in the ocean, historical
regions like countries that no longer exist.
On the physical side, we don't have anywhere in particular to put oceans, drainage
basins, mountain ranges, et cetera.
And I'll say,
as an exchange standard, Darwin Core isn't meant to share absolutely every bit of
data, but some of what we don't have terms for is actually really important for
data users. And so it's problematic when Darwin Core higher geography
is the only place to put important information.
Okay. Let's step back, take a minute to look at why we increasingly need these
ways to share geographic data accurately, regardless of how precise it is.
We typically don't do a great job of standardizing the more physical parts of
higher geography,
as well as the more regionally defined parts like parks or marine
sanctuaries,
maybe in part because we don't have standardized fields to share this data in.
But standardization can be important for those concepts.
For example, you might have a mollusk specimen collected from a given drainage in
2020. It likely has location data that includes precise coordinates
recorded from a GPS unit.
If you have a mollusk specimen from 1920, maybe it only has
the drainage recorded. But either way, drainage is the most
useful concept.
So the quote on this slide is from a freshwater mussel study on diversity and
decline in the United States, where the authors really illustrate what we feel
is the problem. "Unfortunately, natural history collections data
are under-leveraged in taxon-based conservation efforts because much of the
data are decentralized and non-standard."
The others are analyzing species occurrences of mussels by drainage, which
in the US, drainage is a concept that's very well-defined, both
descriptively and geospatially, as you can see on the images on this slide.
But even though the unit of analysis for this study is
well-defined and qualitative, the name of the drainage,
and records from the collection contain the qualitative data, data were not
accessible enough for the researchers to use.
Instead, they only analyzed geo-referenced specimens
because those were the ones they could plot on a map and overlay with the
hydrologic unit data
to assign a standardized drainage name.
So,
half the records in this study were ungeoreferenced historic specimens, and
many did have watershed included in their locality data,
just as text. This isn't necessarily less accurate.
For example, on this slide, Dry Creek is on the label.
That's the same level of precision as a georeference specimen whose
coordinates fall within the Dry Creek drainage polygon.
The moral here, we're missing 51% of the data in this study with real
conservation implications, and many of the specimens left out are
arguably the most important, like the holotype for one of the mussels in this study
where the watershed is recorded as Lewis River, Oregon.
That's too imprecise to georeference, but it's a totally appropriate level of
precision for this research question.
Okay.
So we just saw an example of how we need more explicit ways to mobilize descriptive
information about higher geography. That's this first pain point.
To synthesize a few additional pain points related to discovery, we
can't always georeference, or we can't always do it well.
But how do we make aggregators and users consider data without coordinates?
And then even when we have coordinates, coordinates may refer to different
geography today than on the day the event occurred. So how do we deal with that?
Moving on. Another brief example to illustrate how discovery is affected by
our lack of standard terms for truly basic concepts.
Consider a user who, God forbid, wants to search on GBIF for
records in the Atlantic Ocean.
The Atlantic Ocean is a real place But where do you put that in Darwin Core?
Data providers aren't mobilizing Atlantic Ocean consistently.
Some put it in water body or Darwin Core higher geography, some in
both. Maybe it's only in specific locality for some.
And then at the implementation level, GBIF indexes Darwin Core higher
geography and Darwin Core water body as text strings, which really they are,
rather than as concepts, which really the Atlantic Ocean is.
So a user won't even get all Atlantic Ocean records if the text
they query is Atlantic or vice versa.
Long story short, if you needed to aggregate records from the Atlantic Ocean, you
currently would need to do at least four searches or more on GBIF and compile the
results.
Another complication for data providers mobilizing geographic data is
that geography is fluid. Maps get redrawn, tectonic
plates move. That means geographic concepts are most useful when
associated with time.
For a relatively recent example, Valencia County in New Mexico lost
almost 81% of its territory in 1981 upon the
creation of Cibola County, which occupies the westernmost portion of the former
Valencia County's former area.
So shown here is a specimen record on GBIF that illustrates how confusing such
changes can be to an unsuspecting user.
When this toad was collected, it was collected in Valencia County.
That's what the data from the collection says.
But
the record is georeferenced, and now those coordinates fall in Cibola County,
according to GADM.
Darwin Core doesn't tell us anything about how to decide what timestamp of higher
geography to use, and maybe it shouldn't. Probably it shouldn't.
But again, we're left in a situation where more explicit data would help.
Okay. So then from the data management perspective, we have a few more pain
points.
We just talked about higher geography being fluid and
what to do, what data providers should change or not.
Darwin Core treats physical geography a lot less explicitly than human
geography.
What conventions should data providers follow?
And then finally, the big elephant in the room is Darwin Core higher geography is
so flexible, what do we even put in there?
So what to do about all this unruliness?
Teresa and I wonder if a task group under the Darwin Core Maintenance Group might
be appropriate.
The goal would be to assess current higher geography terms,
maybe look at the difference in terms that are available for sharing human versus
physical geography,
blanket make suggestions for additions or modifications,
look at recommendations for when to use controlled vocabulary concepts.
How do we take advantage of work being done by the Geo Schemes group?
Encourage the use of IRI terms.
Not sure. Anyway, this talk is basically a plug
for if you are interested, please send Teresa and I an
email, and we would be willing to convene a group if we got enough
interest. Otherwise, in the meantime, we'll just keep complaining about
higher geography. Thank you.
You can just go ahead and play the next one.
Hello, my name is Erika Krimmel, and I'm here today on behalf of the team
listed on this slide. In particular, Lindsey Walker, who couldn't
attend the conference, but has been our leader in the work I'm presenting on.
As well as Nikita Salakov and Ed Gilbert, who were the primary developers for
technical work. We'll be talking today about mobilizing rich,
interoperable, and secure fossil data from underserved collections using
Symbiota.
For anyone not familiar,
Symbiota is open source software used to mobilize biodiversity data,
both as a data aggregator and a collections management system.
It's most commonly used by US-based collections, but it has a growing presence
internationally. Most Symbiota portals are themed, and importantly, the
cataloging features in Symbiota largely conform to Darwin Core data standard,
meaning that data mobilized using this software can easily be shared with other
Darwin Core compliant portals and software.
Due to Symbiota's low cost and relatively low barrier to entry,
it's particularly popular amongst smaller and especially under-resourced
collections, as well as with collaborative digitization projects such as those
shown here on the slide. As the user base has grown, it has
become clear that the collections using it overwhelmingly represent modern
biological collections, even though many fossil collections also
would benefit from using Symbiota.
So we recognize this lack of fossil collections in Symbiota as an opportunity and
included funding to encourage paleo adoption in a recent project.
Project has a number of goals, some of which are shown on this slide and/or have
been presented on during prior TADWG meetings.
But in this talk, we'll specifically focus on our enhancements to
Symbiota for actively managing,
sharing, and publishing fossil specimen data.
To accomplish the project objectives, we launched a paleo specific Symbiota portal.
You can check it out via the URL on this slide.
The portal serves as an on-the-ground implementation and testing platform for new
software developments.
And importantly, these developments dovetail with the greater community-wide
efforts to improve the utility of existing cyber infrastructure for
paleontological research.
The new portal is also supported by an existing community of practice in the Paleo
Data Working Group.
Backing up slightly.
Prior to our project start in 2023, Symbiota's features
for mobilizing fossil specimen data were loosely aligned with the Darwin Core
class geological context, and functionality was limited to basic
data entry with few options for data discoverability.
For example
Public portal users couldn't query or export any of the geological context
data. A number of custom fields were added to Symbiota's original
paleo module, which is shown on this slide, at the request of a now
concluded project, but these were never fully documented or tested with users to
fine-tune.
So we focused our project efforts on modifying Symbiota's existing front and
back end to enable user-friendly and accurate data entry.
And over the next series of slides, I'll just highlight some of our results.
One of our first foci
was to capture and publish chronostratigraphic data more
explicitly.
In previous software versions, users were prompted to manually enter all
values associated with geological time.
It's time-consuming, invited errors.
Our project reconfigured Symbiota to use a controlled vocabulary aligned
with the GBIF GeoTime vocabulary, which itself is aligned with the global
standard International Chronostratigraphic Chart.
Now, users can enter the most specific time interval and have the hierarchy
populate. They can also be assured their chronostratigraphic data will translate
correctly to GBIF.
Data providers also have the option to capture geological time values that aren't
included in the GeoTime vocabulary, radiometric dates, regionally
used terms, and these were actually part of the preexisting paleo
module's custom fields.
For collections that are creating and updating catalog records from
spreadsheets,
we set up scripts in Symbiota's internal staging tables to systematically
format data that can't really be parsed neatly into Darwin Core terms.
So verbatim geological context descriptions might include outdated
terminology or uncertainty indicators.
For example, on this slide,
the specimen was recorded as probably Atoka Age with a relative
lithostratigraphic position in the middle of the Morgan Formation.
All of that is important contextual information.
And even though it doesn't fit neatly into Darwin Core, Symbiota can capture it in
this custom field, Stratigraphic Remarks.
GBIF's GeoTime vocabulary was also used to implement Symbiota's new public
search interface for geological concepts data.
Occurrences spanning multiple geological time intervals can now actually be
queried because the back-end infrastructure draws on the
vocabulary's numerical timescale.
So the search results are inclusive, not literal, and this is a
feature that's directly based on feedback from researchers.
The same query principles apply to new search fields
in the map search interface, and then we have this visualization,
which includes a geology layer sourced from the Macrostrat API.
And because geology particularly matters when you're geo-referencing fossils, that
new Macrostrat map layer is also accessible through Symbiota's geo-referencing
interface.
Okay. Taxonomy, persistent challenge for fossil names.
And the new portal is serving as a testing ground for us assessing gaps in the
digital availability of data for fossil taxa.
Many Symbiota portal communities manually curate their taxonomic thesauri,
but we actually chose to source all taxonomy in the Paleodata Portal from the
Catalogue of Life - Extended Release in Checklist Bank.
It's also the source for GBIF's taxonomic backbone.
Doing so has allowed us to actively assess where this checklist could be
improved while we're working with data providers.
So for example, shown here is an issue uncovered during data entry.
Researcher noticed that the incorrect higher taxonomy was associated with their
catalog records,
and via Checklist Bank, we're able to trace the source of the incorrect
information.
So ultimately, we're hoping that by making the provenance of names easily
discoverable from our portal, we can facilitate more researcher
interaction at that taxonomic authority level.
One basic but essential enhancement was enabling the option to set fossil
specimen as a collection's default basis of record value.
That has implications for data use and downstream aggregation.
Previously, this field would have defaulted to preserve specimen, meaning that
data providers had to remember to manually deal with it before data
publishing.
If you happened to see Holly Little's presentation on material entity type earlier
this week, you may be aware that distinguishing what a fossil specimen
record physically represents can be difficult,
even though this information is critical for data use.
So to help contextualize fossil material cataloged in Symbiota,
we opted to leverage Symbiota's custom description field.
For example, here the description is fossil cast, multiple elements.
In combination with this approach, we wanted to mobilize
verbose morphological descriptions, which are particularly common in
fossil vertebrate collections. So similar to how we treated geological
context data,
this information can be imported from a spreadsheet with a script systematically
formatting things as morphology remarks.
All of that can get concatenated in description and then
published via occurrence remarks.
And then this complements shorter anatomical descriptions captured in this custom
Symbiota field element.
Our goal here is we want to capture descriptive information systematically so that
it can be forklifted to a more appropriate field, when and if it
can be handled by Darwin Core.
Unrelated to our project, Symbiota has made recent great developments to support
the extended specimen concept,
like the ability to document relationships between specimens.
We leveraged this work and expanded it for fossil-specific use cases.
So this example shows a common scenario resulting when one organism, this is a
plant,
is split between two or more pieces of rock during the collecting process.
So we call that a part counterpart pair.
Fossil commons have an isolated rock containing multiple fossilized individuals
and/or taxa. In this example, we have one cataloged taxon, a
cricket,
documented in association with uncataloged dipterid flies and plant
material. Using this relationship on SlabWith, the
association between cataloged and uncataloged material can be clearly
defined
and then discovered using both Symbiota's public search interface as well as Darwin
Core.
For specimens referenced in digitally available literature or other
repositories, data providers are able to include links to these
external resources to further extend their catalog records.
And in addition to journal publications,
commonly referenced external sources for fossil collections might be
MorphoSource, MorphoBank, Biodiversity Heritage Library.
We recognize that our new software developments and enhancements
are really only as useful as documentation that
accompanies them.
So to encourage the
adoption of Symbiota for the mobilization of fossil data, all of
these features and workflows are included in Symbiota's official
user documentation, Symbiota Docs.
And we wrote additional documentation via a new
community, Paleodata Knowledge Hub, that was created as part of the
larger funded project. So documentation on the Knowledge Hub builds
on the generalized info in Symbiota Docs with more discipline-specific
information for fossil data providers.
Like example catalog records, detailed workflow guidance, et cetera.
Technical improvements only matter once we have users to benefit from them and test
them. Several existing Symbiota portals, the Tridaphite
Collections Consortium, Cretaceous Vertebrates of Madagascar, International
Taphonomy Reference Collection, those were able to immediately benefit from the
technical developments just described.
And then in the final phase of our project, Lindsay began onboarding collections
to the new Paleodata Portal, which we'll continue to do.
As expected, we had a lot of interest from smaller and under-resourced
collections whose data management needs fall more naturally towards spreadsheet
than database.
But with this portal, we're able to provide them with a tool that's
about as easy to use as a spreadsheet, or in some cases easier, but
really with much better support for managing and mobilizing the full richness of
their data in the context of this broader Paleodata ecosystem.
So that's it. Thanks for listening.
Although I am presenting virtually, two of our co-authors pictured on this
slide, Holly and Talea, are at the conference in Oslo, and they're available if you
have questions. You can also reach us using the contact info on this slide,
and especially reach out if you or someone you know may be
interested in joining the Paleodata Portal. Thank you.
Thanks very much to Erica. Erica's probably up by now, so she
may also be online. But yes, her colleagues are here.
So thanks very much again to all of the speakers, and
we'll transition into a time where we can do a few things.
One, we can ask questions directly to those who have
presented. So if you have a question to direct to a particular person,
that's fine. We can also have open questions,
concerns, interesting things that you got out of the session.
We can talk about that as well.
And we thought we'd start. There's been some chatter on the chats,
and I think Jonas has-
Yes.
And also maybe just to specify it more, I think
all or most of the presenters who had virtual presentations are probably
unavailable. I think it's easiest if you have questions specifically to
them, just put them in the chat, and then they can react
quite easily. Might be technically better than putting them
somehow there.
But yeah, we want to start with two Q&As that came up during
the first block of our session. The first one is a
question to John, so right to the first
presentations, which I hope you all remember.
The question is, John, we might anticipate versioned
data package profiles. For example, GBIF
requiring a Darwin Core data package with an occurrence table,
among other tables of importance to its index,
and so on. Might the Darwin Core maintenance group produce
a registry of named profiles? If so, what might a
governance structure look like for DP profiles?
Checking. Yep, testing.
A
bit of background. There are no profiles now
because our original
pre-feedback was, "Please don't have more than one data model,"
and we took that seriously. So there is only one right now.
But once people started seeing it, especially after Columbia with all those
boxes on the screen,
they started backpedaling and saying, "Can you make one for me and my
stuff?"
So I think we might be heading in that direction, but we haven't talked about
how
such
production would be proposed and managed.
If I were to imagine, I would say that these would have to be
incorporated as additional products for
the standard.
I don't know if everyone's familiar with
what's in Darwin Core, what's not in Darwin Core.
But recently, with our latest public review,
schemas, some existing schemas, have been
incorporated as part of the standard.
This includes all of the GBIF-produced
cores, occurrence
event and taxon, plus several of
the extensions that are obviously just
simple Darwin Core type things.
So measurement or fact, identification history, alternative
identifiers, but not much beyond those things.
Humble extension and chronometric age.
But not, for example, the OBIS extended measurements or facts.
Why? It seems obvious. Because we haven't had a conversation with
OBIS to say if they want us to.
Also, none of the GGBN extensions. Why?
There's been no conversation about whether they want us to.
Here, if there is a
community desire to create profiles, that's a reasonable
thing, but they should be created by the community, and they should
be community-vetted in the same way that everything else is, if they're going to
be part of the standard. So I think that the door
is open to try to do that, but right now we have no infrastructure
for it, no plan for it.
We need to discuss it.
Okay. Yeah. Thanks a lot. I hope this answers the question.
We have a second Q&A question here
online in Vova. It actually affects the presentation that
I gave on Dina and occurrences and
material entities, and the question is: "If GBIF
still required occurrences in order to integrate Darwin
Core data package data to the current occurrence search index,
wouldn't you prefer controlling what becomes an occurrence rather than
leave it to the GBIF interpretation?"
And yeah, I think there are definitely
different views on this.
And really, my presentation was more the
conceptual view, that from a conceptual standpoint,
we prefer to really separate these concepts, occurrences,
and material entities. And I think
from the Dina side, we can say if GBIF
allows this opportunity to provide data without
occurrences, and GBIF
creates the occurrences, this is the way we would go for, but in the end, it's
also, I guess, something that we have to see if it
technically works out.
Yes. Thank you. So we have a follow-up question for Marie,
because we have been discussing this,
but we are unsure about
how,
well, Dina as a particular example or in general, collection
managers, what rules should GBIF follow to
derive these extensions? Should we have an element that
says, "Use this identification to create an extension"?
Or should we have
an if clause like, "Okay, if you have an event, an
identification, and a material,
create this."
So there are a lot of options that
you could take. The only thing that we have sure is that the publisher should
check a box or say, "Okay, I want GBIF to derive this
occurrence from my data." But after that, there are several
options that how can be done. Do you have any
preference? Because we could have a lot of
different rules.
We could have conflicting opinions of where is an occurrence,
and Dina saying, "Okay, did you derive
half of the occurrence in my mind you should have.
What's going on?" So we are wondering what's the best option.
Do you want to take it or no?
I don't have any great answer to that. And I completely understand, right?
There are many different models out there.
There are many people trying to figure out how best, and then we have GBIF who
is
taking that information from us and having to
standardize it in a way that they can show it in an aggregated form.
So it is challenging. We've been making these extensions
for a long time.
Some of them are heavily used, others not much at all.
And I go back to John and the community-driven pieces.
I think we've seen communities rally around what they need.
And even within those communities, there are many different systems and
models,
in order for them to get together in some
planned way for what they need to show.
So GBIF is in an interesting place, right?
And you can also only do so much.
And so again, evoking the communities.
The communities, if you need these things, you really have to step up and work
together, and then work with GBIF to
accomplish what it is you think is best.
Yeah. I think it's nothing we can give the final answer
today. We need to explore it together.
Absolutely not.
But I think what you mentioned, this rule-based set,
maybe including there is a material and there is event information.
I think that this is something we could explore.
Does anybody have comments on that or change the topic?
All right. We have a question back here. Or either way, sorry.
Hi. I have a different topic, if that's okay.
I have a question
based on Tanya's presentation, but maybe to
everyone.
So you discussed how you switched from
ABCD to Darwin Core, and we have also
done a similar thing recently, and I was wondering if
there is still a use case for ABCD.
Are others in the community using it, or what is happening there?
I think that one's for Tanya, right?
Or anyone else.
Is this on? Okay. Hi, Caitlin. Perhaps you can just keep the microphone
because I was not sure about what use case do you mean for
ABCD, because we are having many data published for ABCD.
Yes, but then you said you'd recently switched to trying Darwin
Core to see if that was more successful.
So I was wondering if, in the future, you would still be
looking at using ABCD or-
Okay. Yeah. Okay. I think that's one topic we have to
discuss also in our national research data infrastructure in Germany, where all
collection data centers are using ABCD at the moment.
So we will have to discuss what we will need in our
data portal in the national research data infrastructure, if perhaps we will stay
there with ABCD or if we will change this as well.
The other thing is that, yeah, it's a first try that we now switch to
this other standard or this Darwin Core data package,
and we will have a look how is the presentation in the GBIF
portal as well.
If they're shown everything that was shown until now and some more things, or
what's the difference? So that's something we--
I think it has to be developed, and we will have to discuss it, what we will
do in the future
in our data centers. Yeah.
Thank you.
We can discuss more as a group later.
There was another question.
If not, I have a question.
Okay.
I have a question to Stephen. Thank you very much for this presentation.
It was really interesting to see the path that is NHM London
going down.
You showed a lot of the user interface.
Just a question, how much do you evaluate, or how much
weight do you put on the user interface and on the API?
Is there also machine-readable interface to the whole new
system?
Yeah, there is. So our data engineers, most of the migration is happening through
our API, so we've got a strong API there.
But I think the whole base of the system is actually built very much
with focus on the models that we have and have seen.
So Darwin Core, Latimer Core, all those.
That was the intention as at the start, which is one of the reasons why we've
changed the way and built the way we've built.
I think we showcased the model two years ago, and I sort of focus on another thing
now, but again, I can come back with that, of course, when we're all
done and show more of
the models. So yes, we are focusing on the more technical
interfaces as well,
if that makes sense.
Yeah. Okay. Thank you.
Others? Matt.
So I'll just comment on that too.
One of the things that we're seeing with agentic processes is that
we can spin up new features, and we're getting pull requests from
master's students, and even
people just in the general public.
And so we are having to prioritize that a little bit more, right?
If you touch the semantic layer, then it has to come through the
benevolent dictators for life kind of thing, right?
And if you touch the API,
then how a request comes in, how it's handled, then you're a
little less worried about it
for certain reasons. In the UI, that's where everything is glowing, right?
Now we can
do all of these wonderful visualizations with a couple of very
targeted prompts. Use this visualization, this graph from Apache
Graphs, use these API endpoints to get the data, add the code
in this part of the library, and all of a sudden everybody can play, and it's
very beautiful. But
we have to be more careful at the post level,
to speak
technically, at the writing level, at the updating the database level.
Others?
Just looking across, we've seen several different systems here and
very different interfaces, different models underpinning them.
But one of the things that's striking to me, and coming from the research side
is, the richness of new models, both what's
coming from
GBIF and the data packages and the conceptual model, but also in the
models of the modern systems that are still being developed.
There's a lot coming together, right?
The synergies are there, and I think one of the reasons is because
we can. Instead of thinking of things as just objects
and
managing just a bunch of objects in something, which is what a
lot of people's day job is, we're actually, like science should be, really
interested in relationships between things.
And so, we've been talking about semantics for a long time.
We've gone very much over the deep end for a while.
We've come back, we've gone down again.
So, we're all trying things all the time.
But the relationships are critical, and maintaining-- We
also used to have,
I think, a much more strict sense of what a collection management system was and
what its rules were of just managing things in the box.
And of course, that's all breaking down now for many reasons.
But the relationships opening up also start to cause problems,
because now we're managing links.
We're having to persist things, and we're having to rely on
services that we never did before.
Most of us are bringing in cool services like, "Oh, I want to map something.
Oh, I want to compare my taxonomy against something." And these are great, and they
help the people day-to-day using things, right?
This is great, but the reality is that we want
that extension. We talk about the digital extended specimen. We want the extension.
And one of the things that I struggle with, and Jonas and I struggle with, is
how far do our systems go? How much are you willing to take
in and try to manage yourself versus relying on
services and links and other people to create another great
module where my API talks to your API, I don't have to worry about it So I
think we're at a really interesting time where this is happening,
but there's also a bit of a madness in it that we're all
responsible for containing.
Go ahead.
Yeah, I just want to say I think you're absolutely right.
I think one of the
issues that we've come across is we started
by building these very nice conceptual models.
Based on most of the literature and what had been done in the community.
And when we then looked at the data, because people have been using it over 20
years,
collections are managed
in a multitude of different ways. So where we had a collection object that was
determined as something, we all of a sudden also had
botanists, not a mean word about them, had their collection as an object
directly linked to their taxonomy because their collection was sorted that way.
So you start ending up with these multiple links between the
entities. That doesn't make the pretty model, and all of a
sudden you can transition that model in a lot of different ways
if you don't understand what you're doing with your API or with your system in
general. So
where we tried, we have actually had to extend the model in
various ways just to support a vast amount of data that is
actually already there and the way it's been used.
It's never going to be pretty, but it will work.
It's a work in progress. Nicky?
Yeah, thanks. I just wanted to come back to a point that Matt made and then
James elaborated on. So you talked about getting
effectively a flood of pull requests coming in because people are able to
much more easily make code that does different things within your system.
So they want to enhance your system to do different things,
and I think we've got to separate out the things which are core to a system and the
things which could be plug-ins and re-architect around that, because
we're not going to be able to cope with the flood of changes that people want to
make. But we could
bless certain plug-ins and say we approve those.
If we can take a little bit of the weight off of us in terms
of managing pull requests, I think that
would really be a nice model to follow, and I've seen that model used quite
successfully in other software packages outside of this domain.
I completely agree, Nicky, and that would be a nice
lightweight way of joining smaller centers.
I'll have a
shameless plug about a center talk tomorrow.
But yeah, looking for targets that could distribute risk across
small centers. So I also, James, you were asking about when do
we worry about the links out?
And when does the
research/collection data management system have to pull the data in
and persist it, versus how long can they depend?
There's some very strong evidence.
This community has heard from York Poland before, I think.
That name might ring a bell. That most links will not last longer than
10 years.
So you need to ask your research question.
If you want your extended research, if you want your research to be available in
11 years,
then you can't just conclude a hyperlink, and that's increasingly looking like a
problem when entities like Google are trying to completely
obfuscate the reference to the data amongst
their APIs. So there are real horizons
that appear to be the case just because of link rot.
How many links have you followed that are broken?
And
York has gathered some real evidential data points
there on that front to say, "Hey, yeah, you know what?
In the biodiversity informatics world, 10 years is long. It's old.
It's ancient." So we need to think about that, I think.
Yeah, that's a great point.
Others?
Well, we're quite close to time.
Jonas, any final thoughts?
No, I think everyone is probably tired, right?
It's been a long day. Yes, it has. Had a wonderful day, and we'll do it all
again tomorrow.
So thanks, everyone. This is a great session.
I really appreciate the presenters, but also the audience, and we
will continue to make progress here.
And thank you very much. Enjoy the rest of your day, and we'll see you
tomorrow.